<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: eXcellent | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/excellent/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-07T14:26:23+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Merel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[XSCALE: Beyond SAFe and LeSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/21/xscale/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T20:46:55+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/21/xscale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/xscale.png"></p>

<p>Reflecting our work over recent years, XSCALE is a continuously delivering,
continuously self-organizing, continuously adaptive Agile enterprise
ecosystem that turns all the knobs to ten.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>[This post is currently in draft. It covers most of the ground but the
graphics and some of the text still need polish. I’m sharing it as-is to
garner feedback. You can contact me directly or find a disqus box at the
bottom of this page. Or raise issues on the A:TNG github project if you
prefer. Refer to this draft as V0.5.]</strong></p>

<h2 id="why-xscale">Why XSCALE?</h2>

<p>Over the last decade there have been several efforts to provide enterprises
with a way to scale Agile. The best known are SAFe, LeSS, and the Spotify
Tribal model. Each has its strengths and weaknesses.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">SAFe</a> targets existing enterprises with a low-discipline, top-down,
big-change-up-front, punctuated cadence model that combines Kanban,
quarterly <a href="">release trains</a>, XP and Scrum. SAFe is a good starting point
for more conservative organizations because it’s designed to enable
agility while keeping component silos intact. But this means it shys away
from feature teams, continuous delivery and scale-symmetry.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">LeSS</a>/Agile Path/Enterprise Scrum, etc., are scale-symmetric
alternatives closely based on traditional Scrum. They offer low-discipline
high-collaboration, continuous cadence models that employ <a href="">Scrum of
Scrums</a> to deal with integration and cross-cutting concerns. XP
practices are optional but feature teams are mandatory. LeSS is
big-change-up-front but Agile Path is an iterative alternative.  Specific
practices for product planning, test automation and so on are left for
teams to determine ad hoc. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="">The Spotify model</a> dispenses with Scrum of Scrums in favour of a
pattern of <a href="">Tribes and Guilds</a>, strongly emphasizing bottom-up
collaboration and team autonomy.  It gives even less prescription on team
practices as it rightly expects a structure of top-flight autonomous teams
is capable of deciding for themselves how to evolve the rollout of Agile
practices, but it’s committed to Continuous Delivery and DevOps with every
tribe containing an Ops chapter dedicated to enabling squads to do CD.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>XSCALE includes the best aspects of the older practices:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Like SAFe, XSCALE standardizes team practices using Scrum-XP</li>
  <li>Like Agile Path, it transforms the enterprise iteratively</li>
  <li>Like LeSS, it refactors component silos into feature teams </li>
  <li>Like Spotify it uses tribes, chapters, guilds, CD and DevOps</li>
</ul>

<p>XSCALE offers more than just a refactoring of what came before, adding:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Continuous adaptation using the <a href="">Seven Samurai</a> pattern language.</li>
  <li>Continuous product planning using Lean Startup, Lean UX and <a href="">BPP</a></li>
  <li>Continuous enterprise self-organization using <a href="">Iroquois councils</a></li>
</ul>

<p>But why these specific practices? XSCALE’s intent is to afford enterprises
on all scales an absolute state of the art Agile capability while minimizing
risk of disruption to their existing value streams. So let’s take a step back
and understand this in principle before we get down to nuts and bolts.</p>

<h2 id="xscale-principles">XSCALE Principles</h2>

<p>XSCALE conforms with the <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/10/4-new-values/">A:TNG
values</a>, which form a strict
superset of those in the Agile Manifesto. XSCALE further assumes six
principles that also form a superset of the ones in the Manifesto.</p>

<dl>
  <dt>eXcellent</dt>
  <dd>Turn all the knobs to ten.</dd>
  <dt>Scale-symmetric</dt>
  <dd>Iterate distinctions to control combinations.</dd>
  <dt>Continuous</dt>
  <dd>Use the smallest practical cycle time and batch size.</dd>
  <dt>Autonomous</dt>
  <dd>Use consensus to make decisions and to delimit accountabilities.</dd>
  <dt>Lean</dt>
  <dd>Maximize net ROI.</dd>
  <dt>Ecosystem</dt>
  <dd>Continuous adaptation of the whole to its parts.</dd>
</dl>

<p>Explanation for each of these follows, then the XSCALE practice patterns
that embody them.</p>

<h3 id="excellent">eXcellent</h3>

<p>The term “extreme” in the original XP unfortunately evoked the idea of
recklessness, which wasn’t helpful in the fledgling days of Agile.
Nevertheless the manifesto authors recognized its intent in a principle that
reads, “Continuous attention to technical excellence and good design
enhances agility”. So XSCALE calls such continuous attention “eXcellent” and
sums it up using Beck’s famous XP maxim:</p>

<p><strong>Turn all the knobs to ten</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/knobs.jpg"></p>

<p>XSCALE regards the XP engineering practices, BDD, CD and Feature Teams as
the fundamentals of technical excellence. These patterns interlock to assure
technical debts are paid before they earn interest, thereby keeping the
delivery process stable, predictable and flexible. </p>

<h3 id="scale-symmetric">Scale-symmetric</h3>

<p>Scale is about combinations of requirements, of dependencies, of defects,
and of people. The number of combinations of a set grows very rapidly; a set
of just 10 things has over 3.6 million distinct combinations. Yet golfers
are untroubled by combinations of grass blades. Golfers make simple
distinctions to control the combined behaviours of grass: “the green”, “the
rough”, and so on. They never think about combinations of the individual
blades. </p>

<p>Agile uses this approach when it 
* refactors code into distinct (<a href="">DRY</a>) classes
* automates testing to minimize combinations of ambient defects
* combines people into distinct feature teams to limit interdependencies.  </p>

<p>The Spotify patterns also do it by factoring combinations of conversations
to small meetings with specific concerns. In general the principle is:</p>

<p><strong>Iterate distinctions to control combinations</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/koch-curve.gif"></p>

<p>XSCALE applies this to the challenge of determining which combinations of
business alternatives have most value. Small projects look to a good product
owner for this, but when you’ve got portfolios of programs of projects, it
gets combinatorially hard. As agile works as a hill-climbing algorithm,
continously integrating little stories into a whole, it’s quite happy to
climb a molehill of value when there’s an Everest right next door.  </p>

<p>To control this combinatorial space XSCALE uses the Behavioral Product
Planning games, which make breadth-first distinctions about business
alternatives and then sort them into easily optimized piles. BPP iterates
breadth-first to assure consistent decisions about alternatives at all
scales. </p>

<h3 id="continuous">Continuous</h3>

<p>SAFe promotes Punctuated Cadence over Continuous Delivery, employing a
quarterly <a href="">release train</a> integration pattern. This enables conservative
organizations to keep their component silos, but at no small price:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Increased cost of quality due to deferring regression and acceptance
testing to “hardening sprints”.</li>
  <li>Wasted time in meetings to figure out how to satisfy combinatoric
inter-team dependency cycles.</li>
  <li>Lost ROI from keeping finished features on ice for a quarter</li>
</ul>

<p>Because it employs continuous rather than big-bang transformation, XSCALE is
able to iteratively break component silos into feature teams, and thereby
avoids these penalties because feature teams can use the GitFlow pattern
language for continuous delivery. The principle is simply:</p>

<p><strong>Always use the smallest practical cycle time and batch size</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/sushi-train.png"></p>

<p>XSCALE applies the same principle in its continuous product planning,
continuous stream coordination, and continuous transformation patterns.</p>

<h3 id="autonomous">Autonomous</h3>

<p>Philosophers dream of an anarchic utopia where the only law is the <a href="">Golden
Rule</a>. As the scale of a group increases past the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar's_number">Dunbar
Number</a>, however, social
obligations combinatorially degrade so the <a href="">Tragedy of the Commons</a> leads
to conflicts of interest that must be controlled through more restrictive
forms of society. </p>

<p>Many of the benefits of Agile derive from peer collaboration and team
consensus games like planning poker and retrospectives, and it wouldn’t be
reasonable to call a process Agile at any scale if it doesn’t empower
consensus through games. So the XSCALE principle is:</p>

<p><strong>Use consensus to make decisions and to delimit accountabilities.</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/council.png"></p>

<p>In theory, individual accountability should be applied when the business
cost of delaying a decision is greater than the social cost of failing to
maintain consensus. In practice it’s hard to figure these costs out.
Historically the happiest medium seems to have been the Iroquois
Confederacy, which used unanimous consent at sub-Dunbar scales to control a
hierarchy of peer councils. </p>

<p>Where consensus protocol was violated or timing called for a rapid decision,
per-tribe “war chiefs” were made accountable. This combination of councils
and accountables proved stable at a multi-national scale over a period of
centuries. XSCALE combines it with the Spotify tribal model to scale
consensus decisions while clearly maintaining team and stream autonomy.</p>

<h3 id="lean">Lean</h3>

<p>Lean is often defined as “Minimizing Waste”. Unfortunately that definition
only refers to one of four Lean pathologies, muda. Lean also works to
minimize overburden (muri) and irregularity (mura). </p>

<p><img src="/images/mmm.jpg"></p>

<p>The maxim also admits an ambiguity. <a href="">Lean Startup</a>, <a href="">Lean UX</a> and
<a href="">LSD</a> use Lean to mean process efficiency, but Lean Six Sigma and Lean
Accounting interpret it to mean cost minimization, right first time, and
hierarchical standardization. These latter forms of Lean can appear to
oppose Agile’s focus on maximizing ROI, fail fast, and adaptive
collaboration.  To prevent confusion XSCALE eliminates the ambiguity by
defining the Lean principle simply as:</p>

<p><strong>Maximize net ROI</strong></p>

<p>We say net ROI to account for Cost of Delay (COD), and we represent both
explicitly when adapting the order and design of the work. With this in mind
XSCALE adapts several specific Lean practice patterns:</p>

<ul>
  <li>As a special case of Breadth-first Roadmapping, Lean Startup’s <a href="">business
model canvas</a> to pivot and refactor the enterprise’s value streams</li>
  <li>Per stream <a href="">Value Stream Maps</a> converted to a <a href="">Lean Kanban</a> and
<a href="">cumulative flow diagrams</a> to represent the relationship between stream
funding, stream return, and the stream roadmap</li>
  <li><a href="">Product Teams</a> working cross-functionally per Lean UX to coordinate
<a href="">set-based-design</a> with lo-fi prototyping, BDD and Feature roadmaps</li>
  <li><a href="">Lean Transformation Canvas</a> as a roadmap for the <a href="">Seven Samurai</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>These Lean practices all work to maximise net ROI. XSCALE interlocks them
using scale-symmetric roadmapping to render a stream funding cycle without
resorting to project budgets and baselines yet remaining continuously
responsive to metrics and learnings for the teams in the stream and for the
market for the stream’s output.</p>

<h3 id="ecosystem">Ecosystem</h3>

<p>We have become used to combining the noun ecosystem with the adjective
fragile. This is an artefact of the <a href="">anthropocene era</a> where biological
ecosystems are undergoing catastrophic change. </p>

<p>The prime characteristic of an ecosystem, however, is not fragility, but
agility - that it embraces cycles of change to maintain its productivity
over time.  A living ecosystem differs from a zoo in that it has evolved to
continuously adapt to changes in the populations and behaviours of its
constituent organisms.  </p>

<p>The biological principles are generation and death. Generation continously
produces experimental variations on behaviour, and death removing variations
that don’t efficiently adapt to the whole. In XSCALE we think of Lean
pivoting and set-based design serving the function of generation, and Agile
refactoring serving that of death, but the principle of the ecosystem
remains the same:</p>

<p><strong>Continuous adaptation of the whole to its parts</strong></p>

<p>This isn’t just about products and their features, but also the structure
and practices of teams in streams and streams in the enterprise. This
ecosystem principle turns the Taylorist conceit of all-wise managers and
serf-like workers on its head, leveraging the Agile function of management
as <a href="">servant-leaders</a> to autonomous teams of peer workers.</p>

<p>In order to pivot and refactor the enterprise as a whole, XSCALE relies on a
hierarchy of councils: </p>

<ul>
  <li>chapters as groupings of people with common capabilities across squads </li>
  <li>stream councils steered by chapter representatives</li>
  <li>an enterprise council steered by stream council representatives. </li>
</ul>

<p>At each level there are also some individual accountabilities defined by
these teams.  Each squad in a stream has distinct roles for agile coach and
product owner.  Each stream has a product manager and a stream manager. And
the enterprise has its executive officers. </p>

<p>The accountabilities of these individual roles are defined by treaties
within their respective councils. Likewise the accountabilities of the
enterprise as a whole, and each of its streams, and each of their chapters,
are all respectively defined by treaties in story-normal form. Councils each
use this statement of their accountability to scope their planning using the
<strong>Breadth-First Roadmap</strong> method described below.</p>

<h2 id="xscale-practice-patterns">XSCALE Practice Patterns</h2>

<p>XSCALE is “opinionated” in the same sense as <a href="">Ruby on Rails</a>.  This means
you’ll want to follow its practices very closely to begin with - because this
is how it “turns all the knobs to ten”.  </p>

<p>Because XSCALE isn’t a big-change-up-front framework, as it grows and the
enterprise gains experience with its practices the various councils will
collaboratively vary and augment them. Nevertheless, the following provides
a state of the art starting point.</p>

<h3 id="enterprise-practices">Enterprise Practices</h3>

<p>XSCALE adopts the <a href="">Beyond Budgeting</a> premise that each value stream must
either earn its keep or convince other, self-funded streams that it is worth
their investing some part of their revenue to fund it. This is not to
disempower executives, but to assure that the enterprise pivots coherently
and collaboratively to improve its overall ROI.</p>

<p>Therefore, while we describe the patterns in this section as “Enterprise
Practices”, this doesn’t mean they’re only performed in the stratosphere.
Following the principle of Scale-Symmetry these same patterns used by
streams and squads to optimize their ROI and reconcile same with available
funding.  As a pattern language based on and generating BDD we also refer to
these practices collectively as Behavioral Product Planning or “BPP”.</p>

<p><img src="/images/bbingo.png"></p>

<h4 id="feature-points-story-points-and-normalized-story-points">Feature Points, Story Points and Normalized Story Points</h4>

<p>In BPP we change the unit of estimation from story points to feature points.
Where story points represent only the relative effort required to deliver a
story, feature points estimate increments of funding necesssary to deploy a
whole feature. Because the number of story points that will fit into a
funding increment depends on team velocity at the time of delivery, there’s
no linear mapping between feature points and story points. </p>

<p>This removes the need to attempt to normalize story points across teams.
Instead the Backlog Bingo practice gives feature points an empirical basis
in relation to previously delivered features. XSCALE uses these feature
points both in establishing a reasonable level of funding per business
objective, and as a direct input to the “Royal Cod” prioritization method.
Where it is necessary to represent both feature points and story points on a
stream flow diagram, we simply monetize story points using the formula:</p>

<p>Monetized Story Points = Story Points / Feature Velocity</p>

<p>Where Feature Velocity is the squad’s current throughput in story points per
feature point. If, for example, a squad costs its stream 10 feature points
per week, and delivers 25 story points in the same week, its velocity is 2.5
SP/FP. </p>

<p>This is functionally equivalent to the traditional Agile measure of project
velocity, but because it’s normalized to feature points it makes it easy to
do the arithmetic projecting the various velocities of multiple squads in a
stream, which in turn enables the stream to visualize its activities in a
standardized cumulative flow diagram as described in he Stream Practices
section below.</p>

<h4 id="breadth-first-roadmap">Breadth-First Roadmap</h4>

<p><img src="/images/bfr.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Breadth-First Roadmap (BFR) is a generalization of the Lean Startup <a href="">Business
Model Canvas</a> composed of simple, commonplace Agile practices - story normal
form, INVEST properties and categories of BDD acceptance criteria. Its
function is to concrete shared understanding of a group’s delivery targets or
courses of action, and assure complete analysis of same to a limited depth.</p>

<p>XSCALE applies BFR at an enterprise level to determine what value streams are
required to realize a business model. At a stream level we use it to determine
the features of products and services required to achieve the stream’s
business objectives. And delivery squads can also use BFR to determine the
stories required to deliver a feature.</p>

<p>Therefore every BFR can be regarded as an expansion of a single, larger
<strong>scoping story</strong>.  It’s important to begin by describing this story in
<a href="">story-normal form</a> in order to scope roadmapping conversations to a single
shared intent.</p>

<p><img src="/images/roadmap0.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>At every level, BFR takes the form of a matrix of objectives and themes
where a theme defines a category of acceptance criteria for a cross-cutting
technical, business or user experience concern and the objectives combine to
satisfy the scoping story respecting these themes.</li>
  <li>Each objective expands to a set of sub-features in story-normal form.  These
features are checked to assure their INVEST compliance. Here the S in INVEST
is generalized to mean “scale similar” rather than just “small”.</li>
  <li>The intersection of a feature and a theme is simply a checkbox; each box can
only contain a blank or a checkmark. A checkmark means there are acceptance
criteria for this feature in this theme and a blank means there aren’t.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/images/roadmap1.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>Each feature is evaluated against all themes. </li>
  <li>As each feature is evaluated, also consider whether there are acceptance
criteria in a theme that isn’t yet part of the roadmap. If so, add a column
for that theme and re-evaluate all the features to determine whether they
also have some acceptance criteria in it.</li>
  <li>It’s fine to modify or refactor features as you go so long as all the
roadmap’s boxes are consistently updated.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/images/roadmap2.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>Evaluate each theme to determine whether it is sufficiently covered by
features to achieve the scoping story.</li>
  <li>If not, the roadmap should be extended with extra features to assure the
theme is sufficiently covered, with these features subsequently evaluated in
all themes.</li>
  <li>If it appears that all features have the same pattern of checkboxes for two
themes, consider whether those two may be refactored into one.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/images/roadmap3.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>If a theme has checkboxes for all or almost all features, break out further
features to encapsulate shared technical infrastructure to economically
support the commonalities. We call these <strong>technical features</strong>.</li>
  <li>If a theme has no checkboxes ticked, it may simply be deleted. If it has
only a very small number ticked, it may be better to convert the sparse
theme into a feature.</li>
  <li>In general this  process continues until the team agrees that the roadmap is
complete or there is no more time available.</li>
</ul>

<p>To use BFR properly it’s important to keep “breadth-first” in mind. The
roadmapping process may become long and onerous if features and themes are too
numerous or detailed for the scale of the roadmap. Each feature will be
expanded into a further roadmap at the next level down until they’re small
enough to constitute delivery stories. So it’s counterproductive to
over-specify them.</p>

<h4 id="backlog-bingo">Backlog Bingo</h4>

<p>The original XP Planning Game, now known as “Planning Poker”, is a proven way
for delivery teams to collaborate on estimating the relative effort required
to collaboratively deliver a set of stories. XSCALE generalizes Planning Poker
to make a method of determining the funding required to deliver a set of
products and services. </p>

<p>Backlog Bingo is easy to play:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Write <a href="">Fibonacci numbers</a> from 1 to 89 on cards and lay them out in a row
across a large table. There’s nothing magical about Fibonacci numbers - we
use them because they consistently lead people to think in terms of
trade-offs - is feature A really as big as feature B + feature C, and so on.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Select three previously delivered and deployed features with well documented
costs, one small, one medium and one large. Call these <strong>probes</strong>. Describe
each probe in story-normal form commensurable with the roadmap features you
want to estimate.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Figure out a funding increment that constitutes the greatest common divisor
of the probes’ respective costs and call this a feature point. Place the
three probes under the Fibonacci numbers that match their respective
magnitudes in feature points. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Pick a feature from your roadmap. Compare it with the probes, starting with
the middle one, to evaluate its relative size in Fibonacci multiples of
feature points.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>As you add features, sort them into the appropriate Fibonacci column.
Continue to compare features this way until there are none left to compare.
If the estimators cannot agree on the Fibonacci number for a feature,
split it into pieces they can estimate separately.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Bingo can also be used without a dollar basis to estimate relative business
value. You simply pick a different set of 3 probes - one for an existing
deployed feature that the PO says has low business value, and then one
that’s crticially important to business function, and then one roughly in
between. Place them at 3, 13 and 55, respectively, and the rest of the Bingo
game runs as above.</p>

<h4 id="royal-cod-prioritization">Royal Cod Prioritization</h4>

<p>RoI+CoD (which we affectionately call “Royal Cod”) is a simple consensus game
to prioritise the BFR. It is both easier and more accurate than the SAFe
“Weighted Shortest Job First” (WSJF) equivalent for reasons described below.</p>

<p><img src="/images/bpp.png" width="400"></p>

<p>RoI+CoD uses two Bingo sessions to assign values to the BFR features in terms
of:</p>

<ul>
  <li>effort in feature points</li>
  <li>relative business value</li>
</ul>

<p>Technical team members - developers, architects, designers and testers - play
the first bingo game with Product Owner and stakeholders in the room to
answer questions and also to question any estimate they feel is too large or
too small. </p>

<p>The second bingo game reverses the roles. Now it’s business stakeholders,
SMEs and the PO who work together to estimate business value while technical
team members answer questions. </p>

<p>Only technical team members are qualified to make effort estimates, and only
business team members to make business value estimates. Once each feature
obtains both estimates, RoI+CoD prioritisation involves three steps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Divide the business value number, which represents expected return, by
effort, which represents the required investment to obtain the return.
This yields relative return on investment - RoI.</li>
  <li>List features vertically in order of decreasing RoI. Let the Product Owner
increase the priority of any business feature if they feel has a Cost of
Delay (CoD) that warrants this.</li>
  <li>Once the PO is content with the prioritisation of business features, let
technical team members increase the priority of any technical feature they
feel has a CoD that warrants this. </li>
</ul>

<p>In order to minimize the overall cost of maintenance, a technical feature
should have a priority no more than one rank higher than the highest prioity
feature that depends upon it.</p>

<p>Once the CoD adjustments have been made, record the relative priorities of
the features to prepare them for Roadmap Refactoring, which will determine
how to best fit them given funding constraints and MVP per business objective. </p>

<h4 id="royal-cod-vs-wsjf">Royal Cod vs WSJF</h4>

<p>Why not WSJF? WSJF is defined in SAFe by the formula (Business-or-User Value
+ Criticality + Risk-Reduction-or-Opportunity-Enablement) / Duration. Since
there’s no clear distinction between business value, risk reduction and
opportunity enablement, nor between criticality and Cost of Delay, WSJF
simplifies to (Business Value / Duration) + (Criticality / Duration).</p>

<p>There are several problems with this:
0. It doesn’t makes sense to divide criticality by duration. Work doesn’t
   become less critical just because it takes longer. There is a trade-off
   but it must be made intelligently, not numerically.
-  Without clear distinctions, which aren’t provided by SAFe, there’s no way
   to assure the WSJF variables are independent. This distorts relative
   Business Value in an unpredictable way.
-  By factoring CoD variables and giving them equal weighting, WSJF actively
   prevents intelligent trade-off conversations that would reconcile
   differing assumptions about their importance per feature.
-  WSJF provides no opportunity to account for how combinations of features
   render the individual feature more or less valuable. This is a moving
   target that also calls for intelligent conversation.
-  WSJF doesn’t account for technical CoD.  Some features may have high CoD
   because of architectural concerns or ambiguities. WSJF leaves that out.</p>

<p>All of these problems are eliminated by Royal Cod. Once you’ve factored out
ROI, it becomes easy for team members to agree on the remaining CoD.  And
rather than adding in CoD as if it were linear, which it’s not, it’s easy
for team members to adjust an ROI prioritization by discrete CoD per feature
including technical CoD of technical features. The result is quick, simple and
unambiguous.</p>

<h4 id="bingo-uncertainty">Bingo Uncertainty</h4>

<p>Uncertainty can lead technical team members to refuse to estimate a feature
in Backlog Bingo. That’s healthy - you don’t want a meaningless estimate.
But then they must clearly describe the ambiguities or inconsistencies they
would need resolved by the Product Owner or technical SME in order to
produce an estimate. </p>

<p>If and part of the feature is estimable but another part is not:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the feature is split into two, </li>
  <li>the estimable part is estimated</li>
  <li>a new technical feature is created to represent the work of resolving the
uncertainty via <a href="">spikes</a> or a <a href="">set-based design</a> process.</li>
  <li>estimating the inestimable feature is deferred until the technical feature
it depends upon is completed.</li>
</ul>

<p>If a large number of features are inestimable it’s usually best to defer the
bingo session until the team has had time to work with architects and
designers to nail dependencies down better, or the product owner has
sufficient time to resolve business questions.</p>

<h4 id="roadmap-refactoring">Roadmap Refactoring</h4>

<p><img src="/images/roadmapr.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Roadmap Refactoring (RR) is a consensus game that leverages BPP to enable
product owners to make rational trade-offs between different feature-sets. It
can be used to quickly assemble a release plan to hit a particular date, if
need be, or to determine an ordering of feaure sets to maximize
product-market fit within the funding profile of a continuous delivery
stream.</p>

<p>Like the other XSCALE enterprise practices, RR is a quick consensus game with
very straightforward rules:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Using the BPP prioritization, lay out all available features in columns
grouped by business objective.</li>
  <li>Pick the first column. Pick the feature at the top of the column. Let the
PO as advised by their product team determine whether the objective can be
met without including that feature. </li>
  <li>Continue feature by feature until the PO sees one that, while still
valuable, could be left out without preventing satisfaction of the column
objective.</li>
  <li>All of the features above that one constitute the minimum viable
featureset for that objective. Call them “bronze”. </li>
  <li>Continue to pick features in that column now asking the PO whether the
feature has a concrete quantified business value, or just seems “nice to
have”. Call the former “silver” and the latter “gold”.</li>
  <li>Total how many feature points are in each of the bronze, silver and gold
levels for that column.</li>
  <li>Do this for all columns.</li>
  <li>If fitting to a continuous delivery funding model, POs simply prioritize
the bronze, silver and gold tranches of features across all columns.  Pick
the most important one, then the next most important one, and so on.  Use
the feature points to project release dates for marketing and other
business development purposes.</li>
  <li>If you’re only playing to create a release plan for a particular
date/budget, determine how many feature points correspond to that release.
Now let the PO determine which combination of bronze/silver/gold levels
will maximize deployed value for that release.</li>
  <li>Record all of these decisions as an easy  starting point for the next RR
session.</li>
</ol>

<p>Roadmap Refactoring is played whenever new features are added to the stream
backlog or whenever the PO calls for it. Because it’s such a quick game it’s
also possible to play in a “what-if” mode to evaluate alternative product
plans to evaluate possible responses to changes in market conditions.</p>

<h3 id="stream-practices">Stream Practices</h3>

<h4 id="stream-structure">Stream Structure</h4>

<p>By a Stream we mean a Spotifystructured tribe that self-organizes using a
BFR and Feature backlog, a Stream Flow diagram, an Adaptation Kanban and a
Council made up of Chapter representatives. We call this a stream rather
than a tribe to emphasize its focus on optimizing a Lean value stream.</p>

<p><img src="/images/spotify.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Because the <a href="http://blog.kevingoldsmith.com/2014/03/14/thoughts-on-emulating-spotifys-matrix-organization-in-other-companies/">Spotify
model</a>
supports a
<a href="http://www.bp.ntu.edu.tw/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/06-Alexander-A-city-is-not-a-tree.pdf">semi-lattice</a>
rather than hierarchic enterprise structure, it is more open, more
flexible and more responsive to change than traditional corporate structures.
As Chris Alexander says, “As the relationships between functions change, so
the systems which need to overlap in order to receive these relationships
must also change”. </p>

<p>This is clearly reflected in the Spotify experience where
“We can spin up a new squad to take advantage of an opportunity or handle an
issue without worry about changing reporting structures. If a squad completes
its goals and has no reason to exist anymore, we can dissolve it without
punishing a manager”.</p>

<p>XSCALE augments the Spotify Model with a consensus decision-making pattern
derived from the historical Iroquois Confederacy. This pattern coordinates
decision-making across squads, streams and the enterprise as as whole is
described in the <strong>Continuous Adaptation</strong> section below.</p>

<h4 id="stream-flow-diagram">Stream Flow Diagram</h4>

<p><img src="/images/flow.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Every Stream is intended to generate a return. If the Stream serves a purely
internal function then its return may simply be defined as equal to its
funding.  XSCALE represents the return and the funding for a Stream in terms
of Feature Points on a Stream Flow diagram, a special kind of cumulative
flow diagram.</p>

<p>Note that where we refer to story points here we mean Monetized Story Points
derived by the formula given in the Feature Points section above. The layers
of the Stream Flow diagram represent, from bottom to top:</p>

<ul>
  <li>deployed features</li>
  <li>integrated but undeployed stories </li>
  <li>implemented but unintegrated stories</li>
  <li>estimated but unimplemented stories</li>
  <li>features with stories covered by BDD scenarios</li>
  <li>BPP best fit of features to funding </li>
  <li>squad/stream funding limit over time</li>
  <li>stream revenue over time</li>
</ul>

<p>Stream Flow represents all of these on one consistent diagram per squad.
Because of normalization to feature points these diagrams are trivially
rolled up per stream, and then to the enterprise as a whole. This diagam is
extremely enlightening because it is directly amenable to traditional Lean
analysis of cycle time, latency, WIP, etc. This provides visual and
actionable identification of wastes, bottlenecks, irregularities and
opportunities, as well as their relative magnitudes. </p>

<h3 id="squad-practices">Squad Practices</h3>

<h4 id="devops--cd--gitflow">DevOps + CD + GitFlow</h4>

<p><img src="/images/cd.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Squads are the most concrete embodiment of XSCALE principles:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Per the eXcellence principle, BDD per feature and per story is fully
implemented and all CI and SIT tests pass before any feature is deployed.</li>
  <li>Per the Scale-Symmetry principle, features (defined at this level as
groups of stories that when deployed together will deliver some concrete
business value) are each assigned to a distinct squad. </li>
  <li>Per the Continous principle, sprints are 1 week long. This means all the
sprint rituals have minimum practical batch size and cycle time.</li>
  <li>Per the Autonomous principle, squads use the GitFlow pattern so they don’t
need to wait for another squad in order to integrate, test and deploy.</li>
  <li>Per the Lean principle a feature is deployed by its squad immediately as
soon as it passes CI and SIT.</li>
  <li>Per the Ecosystem principle, Ops forms a chapter that provides consistent
virtualized test environments and production-like System Integration
Testing (SIT) environments, and assures the behaviour of these CI and SIT
environments are equivalent under test. This assures squads collectively
own their code base andconsistently adapt to one another as it evolves.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="lean-ux--bdd--xp">Lean UX + BDD + XP</h4>

<p><img src="/images/xp.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Streams use the Lean UX <a href="">Product Team</a> pattern where product owners from
multiple squads along with, designers, analysts, SMEs and architects work
together to break features down into groups of stories to supply the
delivery squads. To comform with the Spotify structure this Product Team
takes the form of a Chapter.  Whenever the Product Chapter is not meeting,
its members spend time collaborating with delivery squads.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Stories are produced in <a href="">Gherkin</a> format factored to maintain <a href="">INVEST</a>
properties. Squads get together with members of the Product Team every
Wednesday afternoon to estimate its latest batches of stories.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A story with INVEST defects is returned without an estiamte to the Product
Team for clarification. Otherwise the throughput of the Product Team is
graphed on the <a href="">Stream Flow diagram</a> according to the number of
estimated feature points per week.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Squads hold reviews and retrospectives every Friday and task breakout
sessions every Monday, and every day starts with a standup meeting.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="continuous-adaptation">Continuous Adaptation</h3>

<p>As per the <a href="">Seven Samurai</a> pattern language, XSCALE starts by constructing
a “Minimum Viable Agile Capability” - a “spike” squad within a single stream
that forms a model for all those to come.  The spike squad prototypes and
proves that its tools, relationships and processes integrate as an
efficient end to end SDLC by delivering a stream of small concrete features
with real business value.</p>

<p>In other words this is the familiar Agile <a href="">steel thread</a> pattern applied
to organizing an Agile capability. It is fundamentally important to avoid
pain at scale that the spike squad delivers whole end to end features, not
merely components, so that all the technical and organizational fundamentals
are reliably integrated.</p>

<p>To continuously integrate the spike squad with the pre-existing
organization, <a href="">Seven Samurai</a> assembles the first Stream Council from the
lead doers - not deciders - from each of the organization’s pre-existing
component silos.  As delivery squads multiply, these leads naturally
function as chapter representatives on the Stream Council.</p>

<p>Meanwhile progressive senior managers are enroled into the initial
Enterprise Council to provide a one-stop reporting and support shop for
coaches.  As XSCALE is adopted by more streams, their managers will take
part in their respective councils and thereby may become stream reps on the
Enterprise Council. As described below this leverages the Scale-Symmetric
principle to assure consistent, iterative rollout of XSCALE across the
enterprise.</p>

<h4 id="chapter-squad-guild-and-council-meeting-schedule">Chapter, Squad, Guild and Council Meeting Schedule</h4>

<p><img src="/images/chapters.png" width="400"></p>

<p>As XSCALE rolls out it becomes advantageous to synchronize council meetings
so that they don’t cause calendar-stress. XSCALE leverages the squads’weekly
cycle to achieve this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>All of a stream’s chapters meet simultaneously every Friday lunch so that
squad activities aren’t interrupted. Chapters may also meet at other
times coordinating via their Stream Council.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>At the Friday lunch meeting a Chapter selects its representatives for the
Stream Council, which is conducted immediately afterward while squads are
conducting their weekly reviews. To avoid waste, time and location for
reviews, retros and council meetings should be pre-determined and
synchronized.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Squad retrospectives are held immediately following the Stream Council
meeting so that any treaties proposed by Council might be immediately and
unanimously ratified. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Guild meetings are held asynchronously as convenient to the Guild members.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Once a month each Stream holds a half-day full Council meeting for all its
members in accordance with the Iroquois pattern. If ratification of a
treaty was not achieved unanimously in squad retrospectives, the treaty is
shelved until concerns can be ironed out at this monthly meeting. The
Stream Manager may still require squads to temporarily adopt a treaty
until the monthly Council can sort it out.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Enterprise Council, consisting of Stream and Product Managers from all
Streams, along with all relevant senior executives, also meets once a
month to review Stream Flow diagrams and update the enterprise’s business
canvas and related financial plans. The Enterprise Council may also meet
asynchronously whenever one of its members calls for this.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="adaptation-kanban">Adaptation Kanban</h4>

<p>As explained in the Ecosystem section above, Streams and Squads have their
specific purposes distinguished by treaties framed in story-normal form.
Councils and Chapters adapt and expand these respective treaties by means of
Breadth-First Roadmaps that detail how their Streams and Squads  will
organize to satisfy the terms of the treaties that define them. </p>

<p>We refer to this process as Continous Adaptation because it’s not a simple
matter of executing a pre-defined plan.  The BPP patterns are applied to
estimate and prioritize the respective  roadmap using themes drawn from the
Seven Samurai patterns to reflect respective accountabilities and
responsibilities at each level:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Chapters are accountable for the Adoption and Acceleration of practice
patterns by their squads, and responsible for providing Awareness and
Architecture sufficient to support them.</li>
  <li>Stream Councils are accountable for overall Awareness and Architecture,
and responsible for Stream Flow Assessment of their current state and BPP
Analysis of their BFR.</li>
  <li>The Enterprise Council is accountable for Assessment and Analysis across
all streams, and responsible for cross-stream Alignment and, in
conjunction with the CFO’s office, Appropriation of funding per stream.</li>
</ul>

<p>Each council keeps an Adaptation Kanban to track the progress of features
drawn from a backlog it generates by using BPP on its BFR, and cumulative
flow diagrams - not to be confused with the Stream Flow diagrams - represent
progress as the whole adapts over time.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
