<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-27T23:39:44+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[XSCALE: Beyond SAFe and LeSS]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/21/xscale/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T20:46:55+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/21/xscale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/xscale.png"></p>

<p>Reflecting our work over recent years, XSCALE is a pattern language for a
continuously delivering, continuously self-organizing, continuously adaptive
Agile enterprise that turns all the knobs to ten.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>[This post is currently in draft. I hope to finish it today but welcome
feedback both from my TNG compadres and anyone else who happens by &hellip;.]</strong></p>

<h2>Why XSCALE?</h2>

<p>There have been several efforts to provide enterprises with a way to scale
Agile. The best known are SAFe, LeSS, and the Spotify Tribal model. Each
has its strengths and weaknesses.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>SAFe targets conservative businesses with a low-discipline, top-down,
big-change-up-front, punctuated cadence model that combines Kanban,
quarterly <a href="">release trains</a>, and Scrum. SAFe is designed to
permit an organization to keep its component silos intact. So it includes
some XP practices but ignores test-first TDD, continuous delivery,
collective ownership, merciless refactoring and feature teams.</p></li>
<li><p>LeSS is more progressive in some ways, offering a high-collaboration,
continuous cadence model that relies on <a href="">Scrum of Scrums</a> to deal with
integration and cross-cutting concerns. It is still big-change-up-front,
however, requiring an organization to refactor its component silos into
feature teams before commencing sprints, It leaves specifics of product
planning, test automation and so on for teams to determine ad hoc.</p></li>
<li><p>The Spotify model dispenses with Scrum in favour of a pattern of <a href="">Tribes and
Guilds</a>, strongly emphasizing bottom-up collaboration and team autonomy.
It gives no further guidance on method as it expects a structure of
top-flight autonomous teams is capable of deciding for themselves how to
choose, tailor and coordinate the rollout of further Agile practices.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>XSCALE relies on the premise that full XP actually makes scaling easier to do,
not harder, by assuring that technical debts are continuously paid. And that a
large enterprise can easily adopt XP practices by starting with a small
uncompromised XP team using the <a href="">Goose in the Bottle</a> and growing it with
the <a href="">Seven Samurai</a> patterns.</p>

<p>So XSCALE never needs to effect big-change-up-front of portfolios, programs or
component teams, but it still yields a thorough structural refactoring of
enterprise value streams.</p>

<p>As a result, XSCALE creates more Agility than SAFe as its methods of planning,
delivery and transformation are fully continuous and collaborative.  It offers
a more coherent organization than LeSS by combining Spotify <a href="">Tribes and
Guilds</a> with consensus decisioning via <a href="">Iroquois Councils</a>. And it&rsquo;s more
accessible than Spotify alone because it provides an iterative, standardized,
bump-free way to transform enterprise value streams over time.</p>

<p>XSCALE further differs from the other enterprise agile frameworks by embedding
XP in an ecosystem of interlocking Agile practice patterns from Lean Startup,
BDD, Lean UX, Kanban, DevOps, CD and A:TNG&rsquo;s OAPL to leapfrog the enterprise
to the ultimate Agile state of the art. Not because that waves a banner but
simply because with iterative transformation this strategy achieves the
greatest benefit with the lowest risk.</p>

<h2>XSCALE Principles</h2>

<p>XSCALE conforms with the <a href="">A:TNG values</a>, which form a strict superset of
those in the Agile Manifesto. As a practice pattern language XSCALE also rests
on five principles that should likewise be regarded as a strict superset of
those in the Manifesto.</p>

<h3>XP-based or &ldquo;eXcellent&rdquo;</h3>

<p>The word &ldquo;eXtreme&rdquo; in XP was so ill-chosen it became the focus of the effort
to define the word &ldquo;Agile&rdquo; with a manifesto. Yet even now most Agile software
development teams use at least some XP, and the best ones use all of it. So
there&rsquo;s proven value in it. Ignoring the word, what&rsquo;s the value?</p>

<p>XP mainly differs from Scrum in its engineering practices &ndash; pair working, TDD,
collective ownership, continuous integration and merciless refactoring &ndash; which
interlock to continuously pay off technical debt and thereby prevent cycles of
rework. At scale such debts multiply to reduce throughput, transparency and
sustainability. So we could define &ldquo;eXtreme&rdquo; as</p>

<p><strong>Pay technical debt before it incurs interest.</strong></p>

<p>XSCALE takes this principle and XP practices as its base because this
enormously simplifies the challenge of making combinations of Agile teams work
together. The Scrum practices of sprint reviews and sprint retrospectives are
likewise eXtreme in defining and actioning pay down of analysis and process
debt.</p>

<p>So &hellip; if someone you trust asks you what you mean by X, tell them &ldquo;XP-based&rdquo;.
If it&rsquo;s some historical management dudes, tell &lsquo;em it means &ldquo;eXcellent&rdquo; and
play air guitar. And &hellip; party on, dude.</p>

<h3>Scalable</h3>

<p><strong>Maintain scalability by minimising potential combinations.</strong></p>

<p>Scale is about combinations of requirements, of dependencies, of defects, and
of people. The number of combinations of a set grows very rapidly; a set of
just 10 things has over 3.6 million distinct combinations.</p>

<p>The all-hands release planning meetings and &ldquo;town halls&rdquo; in SAFe  and LeSS
fail to limit conversation to small combinations of people and concerns. The
Spotify / Iroquois patterns actively reduce the scope of conversations, so
they support this principle.</p>

<p>Other challenges come from combinations of alternatives. Because Agile works
as a hill-climbing algorithm, continously integrating little bits of
functionality into an existing whole, it&rsquo;s happy to climb a molehill of value
when there&rsquo;s an Everest right next door. Business Model Canvas and
Breadth-First Product Roadmaps assure the combined work of multiple teams
still adds up to a stream of whole features that maximize relative ROI,
respect stream funding limits, generate one piece flow, and comply with MVP
and CoD constraints.</p>

<h3>Continuous</h3>

<p><strong>All cycles use the smallest effective batch size.</strong></p>

<p>SAFe employs a slow quarterly <a href="">release train</a> integration pattern. That&rsquo;s
useful for conservative organizations because it means they don&rsquo;t have to
alter their existing team structures. But several penalties come with it:</p>

<ul>
<li>Increased cost of quality due to phased regression and acceptance testing in
&ldquo;hardening sprints&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Lost ROI from keeping finished features on ice for a quarter rather than
releasing them as quickly as possible.</li>
<li>Surprises and integration overhead due to the large batch sizes involved in
quarterly releasing.</li>
</ul>


<p>XSCALE avoids these penalties by enabling independent feature teams to deploy
asynchronously using the GitFlow pattern, environment mapping, CD and BDD.</p>

<h3>Autonomous</h3>

<p><strong>Use consensus to make decisions and to delimit accountabilities.</strong></p>

<p>SAFe has been <a href="">criticized</a> for its assumption of hierarchical, top-down
decision-making, but LeSS tacitly assumes the same thing. Many of the benefits
of Agile derive from peer collaboration and team consensus games like planning
poker and retrospectives, and it doesn&rsquo;t seem reasonable to call a process
Agile at any scale if it doesn&rsquo;t empower consensus.</p>

<p>People have long dreamt of an anarchic utopia where the only law is the
<a href="">Golden Rule</a>. As the scale of a group increases past the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunbar's_number">Dunbar
Number</a>, however, the <a href="">Tragedy
of the Commons</a> inevitably leads to conflicts of interest that must be
controlled through more restrictive forms of society.</p>

<p>Rationally, individual accountability should be applied when the business cost
of delaying a decision is greater than the social cost of failing to maintain
consensus. This trade-off seems to have been best managed, historically, by
the Iroquois Confederacy of North America.</p>

<p>The Iroquois used unanimous consent at a sub-Dunbar scale to govern a
hierarchy of treaty-making councils. Where consensus protocol was violated or
timing called for an immediate decision, per-tribe &ldquo;war chiefs&rdquo; were made
accountable. This proved stable at a multi-national scale over a period of
centuries. XSCALE combines it with the Spotify Tribal model to scale consensus
decisions while maintaining proper team and stream autonomy.</p>

<h3>Lean</h3>

<p>Lean is often defined as &ldquo;Minimizing Waste&rdquo;. Unfortunately that definition
admits an ambiguity. <a href="">Lean Startup</a>, <a href="">Lean UX</a> and <a href="">LSD</a> use Lean almost
as synonymous with Agile. But command and control frameworks like Lean Six
Sigma and Lean Accounting interpret Lean to mean cost reduction over ROI and
hierarchical standardization over adaptive collaboration. This makes them
unsuited to our purpose in XSCALE.</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s eliminate the ambiguity and give the following as our Lean principle:</p>

<p><strong>Maximize ROI</strong></p>

<p>With this in mind we adopt the following Lean practice patterns:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="">Lean Transformation Canvas</a> to use as a roadmap for the <a href="">Seven Samurai</a>
patterns.</li>
<li>Lean Startup&rsquo;s <a href="">business model canvas</a> to focus and pivot the enterprise&rsquo;s
value streams</li>
<li>Per stream <a href="">Value Stream Maps</a> converted to a <a href="">Lean Kanban</a> and
<a href="">cumulative flow diagrams</a> to represent the relationship between stream
funding, stream return, and product roadmaps.</li>
<li><a href="">Product Teams</a> working cross-functionally per Lean UX to coordinate
<a href="">set-based-design</a> with lo-fi prototyping, BDD and Roadmap Refactoring.</li>
</ul>


<p>These Lean practice patterns interlock to render a stream funding cycle
without any need for project budgets and baselines, but continuously
responsive to metrics and learnings relative both to the teams in the stream
and its market.</p>

<h2>Ecosystem</h2>

<p>The term &ldquo;Software Development Life Cycle&rdquo; is well accepted even though no one
puts too fine a point on the word &ldquo;life&rdquo; here. We mean the term ecosystem to
take this a bit further. As a principle we mean</p>

<p><strong>Interlock practices in <a href="">OpenClosed</a> self-sustaining cycles</strong></p>

<p>This is where our big pricture comes in [&hellip;]</p>

<h3>Team process</h3>

<h4>Lean UX + BDD + XP</h4>

<h4>DevOps + CD + GitFlow</h4>

<h3>Stream process</h3>

<h4>Spotify Model + Iroquois Councils</h4>

<h4>Value Stream Kanban</h4>

<h4>Stream Funding cycle</h4>

<h3>Enterprise process</h3>

<h4>Lean Business Modelling</h4>

<h4>Behavioural Product Planning</h4>

<h4>Roadmap Refactoring</h4>

<h3>Consensus games</h3>

<h4>Business Bingo</h4>

<h4>Chapters</h4>

<h4>Stream Council</h4>

<h4>Enterprise Council</h4>

<h3>Continuous Adaptation</h3>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problem With Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/13/product-funding/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T20:15:15+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/13/product-funding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/nails.png" width="400"></p>

<p>When all you have is a hammer, every problem looks like a nail.  When all you
have is a project management methodology, everything looks like a project.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Most organisations have become very project focussed. Everything is a project.
New release of software – project. Some process change – project. That’s
great. Projects are good. They are certainly better than the ad-hoc approach
we had before projects. But projects do have some drawbacks.</p>

<p>To work out what the drawbacks are, we need to look at what a project is. A
project is defined (by the PMI who should know) as something that has a
defined scope, a defined start and a defined end date.  So projects are finite
in length. Anything without an end date isn’t a project, it&rsquo;s business as
usual.</p>

<p>This defined end date is where the problem with projects lies. In reality,
most of the things we treat as projects aren’t really projects. They have no
real end date. Let&rsquo;s take software delivery as an example. A company develops
a product, let&rsquo;s call it &ldquo;Wonder Widget&rdquo;. They want to release a new version
(WW 2.0) so they start a WW2.0 project with an end date that matches the
desired release date. When the release date is reached, the project team is
disbanded. Then when they want to release WW2.1, they start up the WW2.1
project and so on. Sound familiar? The industry does this all the time. So
what’s the problem?</p>

<p>The problem is that these aren’t really separate pieces of work. Development
of Wonder Widget doesn’t stop when 2.0 is released; it continues. But in a
project-focussed world, the team that developed 2.0 is not necessarily the
same as the team that develops 2.1. Project teams have a finite life. Some of
the key members may be the same but many will be off on other projects (Super
Service 3.5) so the new team has to learn about Wonder Widget from scratch.</p>

<p>Even worse, the Wonder Widget 2.0 team may have left things in a bad state. We
all know how this happens &ndash; schedule pressure near the end of a project. The
team feels stressed. There are still new features to deliver. Other things
start to slip. Like testing and documentation and code quality. All the things
that will make life really hard for the 2.1 team.  The 2.0 team won’t be
judged on how clean they leave things for 2.1, or on how much technical debt
they accrue. They will be judged on how successful 2.0 is – how many features
it has, how well it sells. Everyone knows that 2.1 will have a hard time but
hey, that’s their problem. 2.0 will be a great success.</p>

<p>Sound familiar?</p>

<p>The problem with projects like this is that they aren’t really projects.</p>

<h2>Therefore</h2>

<p>Treat Product development as a continuous activity.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/zipper.png"></p>

<p>One release of a product shouldn’t mess up the organisation’s ability to
deliver the next release. What we need is a Product focus rather than a
Project focus. The team shouldn’t be the 2.0 team, they should be the Wonder
Widget team. They should be responsible for all the releases of the product.
They should flow from one release to the next as a stable team.</p>

<p>Quite obviously this removes the learning stage from the beginning of each
release but more importantly “that’s their problem” suddenly becomes “that’s
our problem”. The team now has an incentive to keep quality high. This flows
on to other organisational benefits like more predictable releases (as teams
are’t blindsided by technical debt left behind by other teams rushing to
finish).</p>

<p>Similarly for change management projects. Running change management as a
project is a great way to ensure that the change fades away as soon as the
project is finished. Change management is ongoing, with no real end date.</p>

<p>Projects are fine for things that are actually projects. But let&rsquo;s stop
treating everything like one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iroquois Council]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/02/iroquois-council/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-02T15:04:37+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/02/iroquois-council</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A scalable consensus game based on the traditional Haudenosaunee protocol of
councils and treaties. Iroquois Councils enable communities and enterprises to
make decisions together without deferring to hierarchies of accountable
individuals.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/parliament.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The Spotify pattern of <a href="http://vimeo.com/85490944">Tribes and Guilds</a> is a
rediscovered social method.  The Iroquois Confederacy used it on a larger
scale than any modern corporation for <a href="http://www.haudenosauneeconfederacy.com/whatisconfederacy.html">almost a thousand
years</a>.  For
two centuries it peacefully inter-operated with European governance in North
America.</p>

<p>These two co-existed right up to the American revolution with the Iroquois
directly influencing the American founding fathers and their new form of
government.</p>

<p>Iroquois and American forms differ in that Iroquois society was based on
unanimity and reciprocity rather than democracy and property. Their nations
were made up of chains of autonomous tribes managed by a cycle of councils
and intermarriages rather than hierarchies of accountable individuals.</p>

<p>Collaborative agreements between the autonomous tribes were called treaties.
To take effect a treaty required ratification, not just by the people
attending a council, but unanimously by the groups they represented. As
opposed to European laws, continuous review of Iroquois treaties was required
to maintain their effect.</p>

<p><a href="">Iroquois Council</a> is a distillation of this protocol. It consists of an
<a href="">Open Space</a> for <a href="">BDD treaties</a>, a decision-making <a href="">Kanban</a> and
reciprocal ratification by participant teams.</p>

<h2>The Pattern in Portland Form</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>Agile enterprises must continously adapt to market forces, technological
innovations and internal constraints. An enterprise needs an efficient way
to make decisions about how to respond to these changing forces.</p></li>
<li><p>Accountable hierarchies are the traditional Taylorist method for making
corporate decisions. Unfortunately they aren&rsquo;t continously adaptive and
frequently obstruct internal collaboration to maintain power relationships,
generating a whole <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?OpenSpace">Anti-Pattern
Language</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?OpenSpace">Open Space</a> is good for aligning
understanding, but doesn’t achieve alignment on decisions.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?IterationRetrospective">Retrospectives</a> work well
for consensus decisions on the scale of a scrum, but don&rsquo;t scale. Scrum of
Scrums doesn&rsquo;t represent a whole interdependent team so SoS retros
experience political anti-patterns including polarization, compromise and
power games.</p></li>
<li><p>Similarly to Spotify, Iroquois society was structured as a matrix of
councils, not a hierarchy of accountables. Tribes grouped into longhouses,
similar to Spotify&rsquo;s squads, with ancestral and generational associations
connecting people in layers across the hierarchy. These cross-cutting clan
relationships work similarly to the Spotify chapters and guilds.</p></li>
<li><p>The Iroquois &ldquo;great peace&rdquo; lasted at least since 1400 and represented such a
sustainable and idyllic model that Europeans in North America including the
American founding fathers <a href="http://www.ratical.org/many_worlds/6Nations/EoL/chp8.html">regarded it as an
ideal</a>. The great
peace was maintained entirely by the method of unanimous consent to
reciprocal treaties.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Use a game of unanimous consent to reciprocal treaties to enable teams within
enterprises and communities to make decisions together.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>As in an Open Space, individuals propose item for discussion in turn. Voting
dots are used to amalgamate and prioritize items, and the law of 2 feet
enables everyone to contribute to all sessions.</p></li>
<li><p>Unlike an open space, individuals identify themselves as representatives of
teams attempting to arrive at decisions to deal with their common concerns.</p></li>
<li><p>Each council session is split into 3 rounds. In each round:</p>

<ol>
<li><p> Instead of just a conference backlog, employ a 6 column kanban to forge
 treaties. As with any kanban, limit the amount of Work In Progress in
 order to maximize total throughput. The columns of this kanban are:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Team learnings</strong> that could be leveraged by the broader community
(Smiley face)</li>
<li><strong>Challenges</strong> a team can’t solve for itself (Red Flag)</li>
<li><strong>Ideas</strong> for the improvement of more teams than just one (Question
mark)</li>
<li><strong>Treaty</strong> proposals that have gained unanimous consent of a session
and are ready for council review (Exclamation mark)</li>
<li><strong>Proposals that have passed review</strong> and are ready for respective
team ratification at retrospectives (Circle) – initially empty.</li>
<li><strong>Proposals that have been unanimously ratified</strong> since previous
council sessions by all represented teams (Trefoil Knot).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Each session attempts to either create or refine a specific output &ndash; a
treaty proposal:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Smiley face</strong> sessions try to come up with a treaty about how the
community can capitalize on a specific team learning.</li>
<li><strong>Red flag</strong> sessions try to come up with a treaty about how the
community can organize to solve a specific team&rsquo;s problem.</li>
<li><strong>Question mark</strong> sessions review a specific treaty proposal to try
to find a way to refactor it and the passed treaties into a consistent
whole.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>Unanimity in each session is required before a treaty proposal is
defined as “ready for review” &ndash; moved into the Exclamation mark column.</p></li>
<li><p>It’s perfectly okay for session participants to horsetrade on conditions
and trade-offs that must be satisfied before a treaty can be passed. It&rsquo;s
also okay for a treaty proposal to suggest modification or cancellation of
some previously enacted treaty.</p></li>
<li><p>At the end of each round there’s a discussion-free review. All that
round’s “ready for review” treaty proposals are read out and moved to the
Exclamation Mark column.</p></li>
<li><p>Now any participant can move an Exclamation mark proposal back into the
Question mark column, but by doing so that participant undertakes to run a
new session in the next round to try to sort out whatever is worrying them
about it.</p></li>
<li><p>Proposals that are not moved back into the Question mark column by any
participant are regarded as passed and moved into the Circle column.</p></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><p>At the end of the council session, the circled treaties affect no one. A
circled treaty must be unanimously ratified by every team – it’s presented
at each respective team retro to be considered for testing and ratification
over the period between council sessions.</p></li>
<li><p>Only treaties that are unanimously ratified by all members of all teams at
their retros are enacted by the council in its next session. These are
moved to the Trefoil Knot column at the start of the session.</p></li>
<li><p>There is nothing to prevent a smaller subset of teams meeting separately to
ratify on a treaty that only affects themselves.  Likewise teams that don&rsquo;t
represent themselves at a council aren&rsquo;t bound by treaties agreed there.
They may join a treaty in a subsequent council or they may agree to work
together by other means.</p></li>
<li><p>Teams that decide to block a passed treaty &ndash; to prevent it going Unanimous
do so by turning up at the next council sessoin and moving it back to the
Question column. The council reviews the blocked treaty in due course as
it would any treaty proposal.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Unanimity or Bust</h2>

<p>Many modern processes have tried to use unanimity and have wound up
running headlong into the <a href="https://www.sciencemag.org/content/162/3859/1243.full">tragedy of the
commons</a>. For
example the UN climate committees are hopelessly <a href="http://theconversation.com/votes-not-vetoes-a-new-way-to-cut-a-united-nations-climate-deal-24288?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Latest+from+The+Conversation+for+9+April+2014&amp;utm_content=Latest+from+The+Conversation+for+9+April+2014+CID_4bbd0a6f6eeb3c8a3d8719978ad1547f&amp;utm_source=campaign_monitor&amp;utm_term=Votes%20not%20vetoes%20a%20new%20way%20to%20cut%20a%20United%20Nations%20climate%20deal">blocked and
compromised</a>. How did the Iroquois deal with something like that?</p>

<p>Looking through their &ldquo;Great Law of Peace&rdquo; they used a system of checks and
balances based on the desire people may have to keep power. It worked as
follows.</p>

<p>Each tribe represented itself via a sachem. The sachems were males chosen by
the agreement of the females of the tribe, with offices that could be revoked
if their females saw them as unfit or disrespectful of protocol.</p>

<p>There was also a special tribe of fire keepers (Onondaga) whose responsibility
ordinarily was simply to make certain protocol was followed properly. You may
think of them in a Spotify context as equivalent to the coaching guild, or
otherwise as an executive round table.</p>

<p>For any question raised to the great council &ndash; say an upstream tribe fouling
the waters of the downstream tribes &ndash; the sachems had power to decide the
matter so long as they agreed unanimously.</p>

<p>If they didn&rsquo;t, then and only then the decision fell to the fire keepers.  If
the sachems wanted to be in charge, they were motivated to find their way to
unanimous agreement. If they couldn&rsquo;t, their opinion no longer mattered and
the matter fell to the fire keepers.</p>

<p>Then the fire keepers had to agree unanimously among themselves before
their decisions could be regarded as binding. If they couldn&rsquo;t agree, no
decision was made. They were motivated to find unanimity because otherwise
the sachems could begin squabbling again. And that sort of thing could
disrupt the Great Peace.</p>

<p>You might think that a particularly feisty Sachem might bribe a particularly
corrupt pack of fire keepers and thereby seize absolute power. If one tried,
however, he risked expulsion along with his tribe for treason and thereby
the cessation of mutual trade and support. This doesn&rsquo;t seem to have ever
happened in the history of the six nations.</p>

<p>Clever fellow that Decanawidah. Shame the UN doesn&rsquo;t work it this way.</p>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>[Assume a Spotify model of tribes and guilds]</p>

<p>Teams use councils to create mutually beneficial treaties. If these teams
cannot come to agreement on a treaty, any team may call for a decision from a
council of a whole Tribe or a whole Guild.</p>

<p>If that higher council cannot reach unanimity, then the matter is forwarded to
a great council of the whole enterprise. If and only if that council cannot
reach unanimity, the amtter is decided by the the company&rsquo;s chief executives.</p>

<h2>Agile Treaties</h2>

<p>As to the form of a treaty, there&rsquo;s a wonderful collection of real historical
Iroquois treaties collected by Benjamin Franklin
<a href="https://archive.org/details/indiantreatiespr00vand">here</a> derived from the
Iroquois <a href="http://www.manataka.org/page135.html">&ldquo;Great Law of Peace&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>Despite idealization by the likes of Rousseau and Franklin, Iroquois laws had
glaring inconsistencies from the standpoint of a Rawlsian <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?TheoryOfJustice">Theory Of
Justice</a>. Privileging the five
Iroquois nations over other tribes caused inequities that eventually ended the
rule of the confederacy. There were also rules of &ldquo;Peace&rdquo; that don&rsquo;t conform
with modern notions, such as,</p>

<blockquote><p><em>If refusal steadfastly follows, the War Chief shall let the bunch of white
lake shells drop from his outstretched hand to the ground, and shall bound
quickly forward and club the offending chief to death&#8221;.</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Nevertheless, Iroquois treaties seem to fit into <a href="">story normal form</a> adorned
with <a href="">Behavior Driven Development</a> scenarios. To bring them in line with
Rawls we&rsquo;d add these constraints:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>To observe the <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?VeilOfIgnorance">VeilOfIgnorance</a>, no
treaty is permitted to refer to a specific individual or group of people by
name. Instead the treaty must refer to people and groups in terms of their
roles in relationships.</p></li>
<li><p>In order to preserve reciprocity, a treaty may not obligate individuals or
groups that have not unanimously agreed to take part in it. This is the
essence of the most famous of the Iroquois treaties, the <a href="http://www.wampumchronicles.com/tworowwampumbelt.html">2 row
wampum</a> that was the
basis of Gene Roddenberry&rsquo;s famous fictional concept of non-interference.</p></li>
<li><p>A treaty among a group of peers may not prevent the formation of a treaty
among some subset of them. Or if the peers are groups, some subset of their
members. This is what the Iroquois &ldquo;Great Law&rdquo; means when it says that each
of the members must still tend their own fire &ndash; that they keep their
respective autonomy. The only autonomy they ever surrender is by unanimous
consent to a treaty.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>&ldquo;Brightening The Chain&rdquo;</h2>

<p>The Iroquois used 3 metrics to describe the health of their tribes and
nations, which they called <strong>the Fire, the Path and the Chain</strong>. These devices
were encoded into the wampum belts that signified treaty proposals, council
occasions and agreements. The three metrics seem to apply equally well to
the state of health of Agile teams in a modern enterprises so we&rsquo;ll dig in
here in some depth.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/iroquois.png"></p>

<p><strong>The Fire</strong> indicates the quality of internal self-organisation of a tribe or
guild.  Iroquois chiefs were charged with keeping the fire lit and the
fireplace clean in much the same way as Scrum Masters are charged with
keeping team meetings prompt and Lean black belts value the cleanliness and
order of a manufacturing workplace. When a tribe suffered attrition due to
warfare, marriage or aging, its fire was said to burn low, and this was a
matter for resolution at a &ldquo;Condolence Council&rdquo;, which was basically an
agreement among longhouses or tribes to re-balance their membership, territory
and/or resource profile.</p>

<p><strong>The Path</strong> indicated the channels whereby the tribal unit interacted with
its peers. Forest diplomacy entailed a regular cycle of meetings involving
treaties, condolence, trading, inter-marriage and reciprocal gift-giving known
as &ldquo;potlatch&rdquo;.  This last being very similar to modern conferences, lean
coffees, open spaces and meetups. A commonplace subject of treaties occurred
when a tribe&rsquo;s <em>path</em> was obstructed by physical or political barriers,
including but not limited to the movement of tribal borders through warfare.</p>

<p><strong>The Chain</strong> indicated the external integrity of relations between a tribal
unit and its peers. Unlike modern legal systems, Iroquois treaties were held
to naturally decay over time, requiring continuous re-appraisal, refactoring
and re-affirmation to maintain their effect. Treaty relations that had decayed
were said to have rusted, where those still in force were iron, and those
recently re-affirmed were silver. Under conditions of disruptive market
change, technological innovation and internal refactoring, it is a given that
enterprises should revisit their internal assumptions and agreements in a
similar way, and this is the intent of the Iroquois Council pattern.</p>

<p>The chain began with a single family. Faced with an unforgiving environment,
Iroquois families could not be maintained in the isolated, nuclear form with
which we&rsquo;re most familiar in the West. Instead they took the form of line
marriages where a series of exogamous marriages among adults drawn from
different lineages occupied a single dwelling called a longhouse, an
arrangement Robert Heinlein explores in his &ldquo;The Moon is a Harsh Mistress&rdquo;.</p>

<p>While the Spotify model draws on this tradition, the Iroquois were more formal
about chain structuring than Spotify, with each tribe forming a link with two
peers modeled after the row of families in the Longhouse.</p>

<p>Brightening the Chain therefore began at the level of a single tribal unit,
then a council involving two further tribal units. Thus chains brightened
by councils occurring at all levels, with each level maintaining pure autonomy
from the one above it, as limited only by treaties.</p>

<h2>The Councils of Github?</h2>

<p>An obvious question is how this kind of system can be enacted in a modern
online social network, specifically github. It is fair to think of a github
pull-request as a treaty proposal, but there is no equivalent of a
council system on github today. Instead collaborators either work
together in a single repository, effectively functioning as a single tribe, or
assemble a feudal hierarchy of forks, sometimes hubbing on one base, or in
larger projects constituting an informal management hierarchy.</p>

<p>Work is going on within the Agile:TNG group to create a protocol, eventually
to be automated, whereby a system of branches can represent the different
states in the council kanban, with a central repository pulling from
forks as governed by the council protocol described above.</p>

<p>A key challenge to be surmounted in effecting this is the protocol to
apply to the distinction between a fork and a collaborator where the latter
signifies a trusted and invited party but the former may represent an
untrusted, uninvited or even inimical one.</p>

<p>In general github, as a do-ocracy, provides straightforward social methods for
participants to cross from the status of fork to collaborator, but it remains
to arrange a council protocol that uses this as a channel.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Goose In The Bottle]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T11:31:11+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Take a newly hatched baby goose. Poke it down the neck of an empty saki bottle
and feed it till it&rsquo;s grown. Without killing the goose or breaking the bottle,
how do you get the goose out of the bottle?</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/gib.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the problem and the solution in context and leave the riddle
till after.</p>

<h2>Pattern in Portland Form</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>A team can only change as quickly as its most conservative member. A program
of component teams or an organization of silos can only change as rapidly as
its most conservative part.</p></li>
<li><p>Every team has its progressives. If they&rsquo;re empowered, they foster
change. If they&rsquo;re disempowered, they&rsquo;re still eager to take part in change.</p></li>
<li><p>Middle managers account for costs and apologise for slippage. They&rsquo;re used
to that. Telling them to account for ROI and taking away their apologetic
method causes the infamous <a href="">Frozen Middle</a> anti-pattern.</p></li>
<li><p>Taking a team, program or organization part-way Agile offers questionable
benefit and creates risks of failure and reversion to tradition. Taking part
of it part-way reduces the benefit and amplifies the risks.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t attempt to make an enterprise become Agile. Nor a program, nor a
project, nor a team.</p>

<p>Instead, create a new cross-functional end-to-end feature based Agile
capability uncompromised by existing ways of working.</p>

<p>Staff it with progressives And grow it with the support of a coordination
scrum of lead doers from the old organisation with the blessing of senior
management.</p>

<p>Let it leverage the quickest dirtiest deployment pathway but make it
accountable for its own quality.</p>

<p>Add product owners focused on maximising ROI per release rather than
minimising variance to baseline.</p>

<p>Put in place bottom-line metrics to demonstrate that the throughput, quality
and ROI of the new capability exceeds the performance of the old.</p>

<p>Never ask anyone to join the new capability, but let the best people do so,
backfilling the old organisation if necessary, letting it diminish otherwise.</p>

<h2>Zen Riddles</h2>

<p>The Goose in the Bottle is what the Japanese Zen tradition calls a <em>koan</em>, a
kind of riddle for personal transformation. It&rsquo;s not supposed to have a
rational answer.</p>

<p>Solving it is supposed to take sweat. You may have to travel. Consult wise
people. Spend days in silent meditation. Raise children and learn from them.
Grok out.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;re a busy person, however, and this is about Agile, not Zen, so I&rsquo;ll just
give you the answer so we can move on.</p>

<h2>The Coach in the Bottle</h2>

<p>I first read the goose koan as a young man. I puzzled over it for weeks but
then set it aside.  Who has time for a riddle with no answer? I thought it
could have no practical importance and I had no shortage of more interesting
questions to worry about.</p>

<p>Until, as a coach, I became a goose.</p>

<p>I accepted a role transforming a business unit of the largest Australian
insurer. A year earlier I had successfully transformed an insurance BI group
of about seventy. Now I had three hundred staff stuck in silos and component
layers, with myself the sole coach charged with getting them out.</p>

<p>This insurer had attempted ad-hoc Agile twice. Its first project went cowboy,
shipping 5 months late with 1200 defects and zero documentation. The second
project used Agile to fail fast, demonstrating its business case didn&rsquo;t stand
up. For which learning it was blamed and shamed, and its excellent
Scrum-master got handed her hat.</p>

<p>I naturally expect to walk into this kind of thing. A coach is only engaged
when management strikes a problem it can&rsquo;t solve without a coach. You expect to
walk into trouble, or else you won&rsquo;t be there in the first place.</p>

<p>Per the <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/">seven samurai</a> I
set about assessing and aligning senior business and delivery management and
also technical leads per silo.  That&rsquo;s when I hit the wall. People were happy
to engage with me, but I was getting the same conversation over and over. Six
times in a week according to my diary.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I completely agree with you,&rdquo; they said. &ldquo;Agile is great. If we could do
it properly, life would be much better. But you&rsquo;ll never get <em>them</em> to do it.&rdquo;</p>

<p>They&rsquo;d point out another team. I would talk to that team and <em>they</em> would say
the same about further teams, who would point back at teams I&rsquo;d already spoken
to.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t blamestorming &ndash; it was respect for their conservative co-workers.
Each team has conservatives and progressives, and no team can change faster
than its most conservative member. The progressives had learned that through
bitter experience.</p>

<p>That was the bottle, and I was the goose.</p>

<h2>Grow a Better Gosling</h2>

<p>Some mornings I woke in a cold sweat. I realised we were all geese in some
way. The managers who hired me, the progressives who wanted change, but
the conservatives too. They all made up each others&#8217; bottle.</p>

<p>In my previous role, on a smaller scale and with sufficient executive support,
I had been able to break a bottle. But this one was too strong. I wasn&rsquo;t going
to kill the goose by quitting either. So now I really needed an answer &hellip; how
did those old Zen guys get their damned goose out of their damned bottle?</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lovely and controversial Zen book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Sound-One-Hand-Answers/dp/0465080782">The Sound of the One
Hand</a>, which
poses answers to 281 Zen Koans. It offers the following for this one:</p>

<p><strong>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s out!&rdquo;</strong></p>

<p>I found that answer a little unhelpful. In fact I have yet to derive any
assistance from that book in regard to any koan. Which is to say it&rsquo;s a
really great zen book and I highly recommend it.</p>

<p>In a flash, enlightenment occurred, that experience Zen students spend
their time desperately attempting to attain. Or if it wasn&rsquo;t enlightenment, it
would do until enlightenment came along.</p>

<p><em>Take a baby goose, a newly hatched gosling. Feed it outside the bottle until
it&rsquo;s full grown. Feel your heart swell as you watch it flying away.</em></p>

<p>This is to say, don&rsquo;t attempt to make an enterprise become Agile. Nor a
program, nor a project, nor a team. Instead, create a new cross-functional
end-to-end feature based Agile capability for the enterprise uncompromised by
any existing ways of working. And then grow it.</p>

<p>Feed it a budget, requirements, and team members drawn from the progressive
people you&rsquo;ve assessed in interviews. Form a coordination scrum of stream
leaders from the old organisation, empowered by senior management not to
change how the old organisation works, but just to support the new capability.</p>

<p>Let the new capability leverage the quickest dirtiest deployment pathway that
exists for hotfixing. Make them accountable for their own quality and go whole
hog on virtual environments and test-first automation. Use a DVCS to manage
integration between old and new rationally. Add  product owners focused on
maximising ROI in the backlog rather than minimising variance to baseline.</p>

<p>Coach this tiny new capability to produce just the minimum amount of
documentation necessary to satisfy their own operational members. Don&rsquo;t call
it a goose, but something completely innocuous, &ldquo;the small changes team&rdquo; or
similar.</p>

<p>Put in place bottom-line metrics to demonstrate that the throughput, quality
and ROI of the new team far exceeds the performance of teams in the jugged
goose.  Promote and leverage their wins to gain them more requirements from
the business.</p>

<p>Never ask anyone to join the new capability, but let the best people do so,
backfilling the old organisation if necessary, letting it diminish otherwise.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I coached. Over the course of a year that first gosling grew
organically, splitting and splitting again. Business people saw concrete
benefit and flocked together. The coordination forum used this as a model to
create similar goslings. They grew fat and laid golden eggs &hellip;</p>

<h2>The Ugly Duckling</h2>

<p>Two years later the insurer&rsquo;s senior management turned up at Australia&rsquo;s
largest Agile conference to trumpet their wins. Still I wondered &ndash; is this a
reproducible pattern? I soon had a chance to find out.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very large bank, the twentieth largest corporation in the world.
Long before that insurance gig I&rsquo;d been engaged as a coach to take a couple of
its projects Agile. I didn&rsquo;t use the <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/">seven
samurai</a> then, just got
stuck in and went for it.</p>

<p>While we made progress we were stopped by unaligned senior management when
they found out what we were up to.  My coaching sponsors were none too pleased
that I hadn&rsquo;t addressed alignment before moving onto adoption. The
experience turned ugly and I never expected to be invited back.</p>

<p>Well, never say never. Six years later I was re-engaged by the same senior
manager who&rsquo;d handed me my hat. We had both learned some important things in
the interim, and he had an ad-hoc Agile project in the online division that
was struggling.</p>

<p>This project was for a ground-breaking product, but it was perceived to have
under-delivered its first release with severe quality problems. I found all
manner of waste, stress, compromise and misalignment. But there was one great
advantage. This product was regarded as special. That little team was already
out of the bottle.</p>

<p>Over the next 18 months I aligned the rest of the business unit to support the
new capability and mentored the team directly to consistently exceed their
metrics release on release. The product won a dozen external awards and the
team received the Group CIO award for best project in the bank.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t all me of course &ndash; the team members were all-stars. And it was never
a perfect project. There were hard yards to make. Nevertheless, realignment of
delivery pipeline, team structure and environment management that resulted
became a model to be leveraged. First within the online program, then within
its business unit, and then throughout the bank.</p>

<p>Sorry, but I can&rsquo;t resist talking about the waterfowl method here &hellip;
comparing Agile in the bank with Aesop&rsquo;s <a href="http://hca.gilead.org.il/ugly_duc.html">ugly
duckling</a> who grew up &hellip;  and then
everyone saw it as a beautiful swan &hellip;</p>

<h2>Will it Zen?</h2>

<p>In a <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/The+Goose+in+the+Bottle">conversation with Alistair
Cockburn</a> I explained my
experience with this Goose In the Bottle pattern. He worried that I had
&ldquo;[broken] the question’s presupposition by cheating and getting a new goose,
hence not answering the question, but still ending up a free goose.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I wanted to point Alistair at the <a href="http://www.markability.net">laws of form</a>
but I didn&rsquo;t get time. Of course it requires only a moment&rsquo;s thought to
realize there can never be a real goose in a real bottle. If you did it
to a real gosling, it would perish long before it grew old enough to poke
its head out. Our goose was always a metaphor.</p>

<p>On the zen of it, the moment you hear this koan some part of you becomes the
goose, and the koan your bottle. Like all koans, to get out you have to change
who you are.</p>

<p>The bottle doesn&rsquo;t break &ndash; the old organisation never changes. The goose
doesn&rsquo;t have to be killed &ndash; neither in the bottle nor out of it. But as you
feed the goose outside more requirements and more budget and more people,
soon there is no goose left in the bottle. Nor a bottle for it to be in.</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s out!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Seven Samurai]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T21:53:27+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A pattern language for enterprise agile transformation.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Agreement.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Enterprise agile is a phrase that&rsquo;s bandied about a lot.  Sounds like a good
thing, but why would you want it, what is it, and how do you get it? This
pattern language answers those questions.</p>

<p>In a nutshell, enterprise agility means continuous adaptation. As nature amply
demonstrates, organisations that can&rsquo;t continously adapt are rapidly
outcompeted by those that can. That&rsquo;s why you want it.</p>

<p>Continuous adaptation internally as capabilities and teams evolve. Continuous
adaptation externally to customer experiences, market forces and technological
innovations. And continuous adaptation in relating these two to maximise
your enterprise&rsquo;s ROI. That&rsquo;s what it is. The remaining question is how.</p>

<h2>Spoilers</h2>

<p>Akira Kurosawa&rsquo;s cinematic masterpiece provides a great <a href="">system metaphor</a>
for a continuously adaptive enterprise. And that&rsquo;s why we&rsquo;re making it the
fundamental pattern language of the <a href="">OAPL</a>.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to see the film to understand this pattern language, but its
patterns necessarily involve spoilers for the film. So you may want to see it
first if you haven&rsquo;t already. The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zNqQXC8Tv8U">restored 207-minute
version</a> is freely available
through the usual torrent sites.</p>

<p>From here on out we&rsquo;ll leave the question of spoilage up to you, gentle
reader. Note also that at present several of the links below are broken &ndash;
we&rsquo;re still putting the more detailed patterns together but have put this
draft up now to generate feedback.</p>

<h2>The Film</h2>

<p>The Seven Samurai concerns a defenceless village that hires a group of
down-at-heel samurai as protection against a horde of bandits. The samurai
transform the village into a self-organising force that destroys the bandits
and takes ownership of its own destiny.</p>

<p>The popular image of samurai as armored warriors is quite different to their
depiction here. Kurosawa&rsquo;s samurai are master strategists, coaches of the
first water. Their transformation involves eight distinct strategic patterns,
each augmented by more specific tactical patterns. A:TNG has discussed its
approach to construction of an Agile pattern language <a href="">here</a> and we use the
<a href="http://c2.com/ppr/about/portland.html">Portland Form</a> to represent these
patterns.</p>

<p>Why eight patterns when there are only seven samurai? Simply, the last pattern
is for the enterprise to take ownership of its own transformation as coaching
becomes irrelevant. As in the film, it&rsquo;s the village that wins, not the
samurai.</p>

<hr />

<h2>The Patterns</h2>

<h4>Continuous Assessment</h4>

<p>Motivate Agile in terms of bottom line metrics.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Assessment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Many organisations embark on Agile ad-hoc, at grass roots level, without
clearly understanding real drivers, benefits and challenges.</p></li>
<li><p>Enterprise architecture and business constraints can prevent Agile
transformation from succeeding. Some enterprises may not be ready to
commit to addressing these constraints.</p></li>
<li><p>Teams, programs and business units may begin a transformation without
realising their organisation isn&rsquo;t ready, and this may lead them to fail.</p></li>
<li><p>Prominent failures may forestall a successful transformation, creating the
perception that Agile &ldquo;might work elsewhere but can&rsquo;t work here&rdquo;.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Interview stakeholders to construct preliminary value stream maps of delivery
and business activities. Validate these by attending the represented
activities and constructing cumulative flow metrics for them.</p>

<p>Represent as diagrams to motivate urgent concern about waste, stress,
irregularity and misalignment. Determine critical numbers that represent real
improvements to throughput, quality and ROI.</p>

<p>Construct a preliminary plan detailing targets for these critical numbers with
a draft timeframe and budget necessary to transform to a Minimum Viable Agile
Capability (&ldquo;MVAC&rdquo;) that would meet these targets, at least on a small scale.
Assess maturity of existing Agile teams using the <a href="http://comparativeagility.com">Cohn&rsquo;s Comparative Agility
metrics</a>, and reconcile with this MVAC.</p>

<p>See also <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle/">Goose in the
Bottle</a></p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Alignment</h4>

<p>Enrol decision makers as Product Owners in a Strategic Scrum.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Alignment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Component silos, matrix management, waterfall baselines and phase gates,
project based cost accounting and middle management hierarchies can make it
difficult for an organisation to achieve and maintain Agile benefits.</p></li>
<li><p>There are further alignment issues inherent in a transformation program.
Progressive/conservative antagonism, disagreements over change scope and
ownership, confusion over metrics and trade-offs, as well as the <a href="">FUD</a>
induced by piecemeal change &hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>Enterprise misalignments are commonly associated with the anti-patterns
we call <a href="">enterprise smells</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Ad hoc Agile teams can&rsquo;t address such alignment issues because they don&rsquo;t
have adequate executive support to change the process of other teams or the
way they interoperate.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Induce progressive senior executives to meet regularly in a collaborative
&ldquo;Strategic Scrum&rdquo; that will maintains product ownership for the
transformation.</p>

<p>Ideally execs are motivated to participate by pre-existing C-level support.
Such support is seldom reliable at the start of a transformation, however, and
it may be an urgent priority of the Strategic Scrum to represent sufficient
drivers to clearly establish its ownership of a transformation initiative.</p>

<p>As with Agile delivery, the senior member of this scrum is identified as Chief
Product Owner for the transformation, with the others dubbed <a href="">Operational
Product Owners</a>. This Strategic Scrum provides a way for the executives to
immediately experience agile for themselves and to <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?EatYourOwnDogfood">&ldquo;eat their own
dogfood&rdquo;</a>. Over the course of
the transformation it will provide a one stop shop into which coaches and
organisational change agents report progress.</p>

<p>An important first step for the Strategic Scrum is selecting one or more
alignment patterns to form the initial stage of the transformation:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle/">Goose in the
Bottle</a></li>
<li><a href="">Inversion of Control</a></li>
<li><a href="">Tribes and Guilds</a></li>
<li><a href="">Capability Funding</a></li>
<li><a href="">Lean before Agile</a></li>
<li>&hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>See also <a href="">Behavioural Product Planning</a>, <a href="">Feature Based Teams</a>
<a href="">Guiding Coalition</a>, <a href="">Influence the Influencers</a></p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Analysis</h4>

<p>Form a Coordination Scrum from coaches and delivery and operational stream
leads.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Analysis.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Once an enterprise has assessed its as-is state and aligned executives
to support its transformation, there is an immediate desire for a detailed
&ldquo;to-be&rdquo; vision and a plan to get there. This is often called an OCM
(&ldquo;Organisation Change Management&rdquo;) plan.</p></li>
<li><p>Under time pressure the people accountable for OCM may feel safest picking a
one-size-fits-all framework and idealistic &ldquo;to-be state&rdquo; vision. This is
a waterfall approach to transformation &ndash; what XP used to call &ldquo;Big Design
Up Front&rdquo; or &ldquo;BDUF&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>Sounds nasty but why is it actually bad? BDUF focus on vision and
framework maximises WIP and results in dysfunctional transition states where
delivery and business metrics consistently worsen. This obviously raises
risks and can cause executive support for transformation to tail off.</p></li>
<li><p>OCM plans may also be applied in a non-collaborative &ldquo;they change, we
don&rsquo;t&rdquo; mindset. If change agents are not also change recipients they are
insensitive to the wisdom of the doers causing widespread <a href="">FUD</a> and politics.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>To make an enterprise Agile, we emphasise that change planning must be Agile.
What&rsquo;s needed isn&rsquo;t a precise vision but a disciplined collaboration cycle for
a funded Coordination Scrum that includes existing stream leads. That&rsquo;s to say
lead doers, not middle-management deciders, along with experienced coaches to
provide sound advice on tactical concerns over the course of the transformation.</p>

<p>The Coordination Scrum represents its work on an <a href="">Agile Transformation
Roadmap</a> from which coaches derive a <a href="">Coaching Kanban</a> that prioritises
and tracks their team-based coaching activities, and which is iteratively
reviewed by the transformation product owners of the Strategic Scrum.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Awareness</h4>

<p>Organise change recipients into a system of <a href="">Guilds and Tribes</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Awareness.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Change plans usually begin with training for the doers on new ways of
working.  This includes role-specific skills and education on the tools
necessary to new roles.</p></li>
<li><p>Awareness as a process isn&rsquo;t merely a matter of training, but ongoing
agreement about ways of working, For the transformation to become
sustainable, doers must own and direct the change stories themselves.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Organise people of common capabilities into &ldquo;Guilds&rdquo; and people collaborating
on common business and delivery streams into &ldquo;Tribes&rdquo;. Let coaches work with
these teams to plan and effect change using a repeating cycle of Scrum
<a href="">retrospectives</a> and, at scale, <a href="">agile parliaments</a>.</p>

<p>These consensus protocols spread awareness of the drivers and methods for new
ways of working, and feed decisions, agreements and concerns back into the
Coordination Scrum.</p>

<p>Coaches use role-playing games to raise Guild and Tribe awareness of Agile
methods and their respective parts in the transformation.  The Coordination
Scrum also works with the Strategic Scrum to obtain support to empower tribes
and guilds to make their own decisions to enable rapid change.</p>

<p>Once they&rsquo;re up to speed, add Guild and Tribe representatives to the
Coordination Scrum. If scale requires it, the Coordination Scrum may evolve
into a Guild in its own right.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Architecture</h4>

<p>Guilds institute technical enablers for feature based delivery.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Architecture.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Technical enablers and structural transformations must be adopted by
change recipients to enable new ways of working.</p></li>
<li><p>Change patterns promoted by the Coordination Scrum have to be grounded and
tailored into stories that fit the immediate necessities of the as-is
enterprise.</p></li>
<li><p>Change stories that requires anyone to put down their tools and stand idle
will be immediately opposed by the guild system and business stakeholders.</p></li>
<li><p>Collaborative coaching is necessary to assure change recipients are ready
and motivated to work in the new way</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Prioritize technical enablers in the Coaching Kanban including but not limited
to:</p>

<ul>
<li>work-management and knowledge-management tools</li>
<li>test data fixtures and service mock objects</li>
<li>BDD tooling and integration of same into dev workflow</li>
<li>virtual environments sufficient for Continuous Delivery</li>
<li>version control systems suitable for distributed integration.</li>
</ul>


<p>At an enterprise level, Guilds stage the structural alignment patterns
determined by the Strategic Scrum, assure existing component teams are primed
to support if not adopt the new ways of working, and that scarce technical
resources or SMEs are adequately available for new delivery capabilities to
come on line.</p>

<p>Guilds adopt, specialise, adjust and refactor architectural patterns
iteratively as they gain experience with the benefits and challenges.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Adoption</h4>

<p>Track transformation stories in a coaching kanban.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Adoption.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Coaching shepherds product planning and delivery teams through the same
Samurai patterns as it does for the enterprise, just on a smaller scale.</p></li>
<li><p>A well formed transformation plan involves a backlog of <a href="">Transformation
Stories</a> motivated by drivers identified by <a href="">Operational Product Owners</a>
from the Strategic Scrum.  These stories should have the <a href="">INVEST</a>
properties and be expected to demonstrate value by improving
<a href="#Assessment">Assessment</a> metrics.</p></li>
<li><p>ROI for Agile transformation is maximized when transformation stories are
detailed and delivered iteratively, minimizing <a href="">Work In Progress</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Value delivery begins as the <a href="">Product Planning Scrum</a> builds a
breadth-first product roadmap and an initial product backlog along with a
<a href="">Steel Thread</a> sufficient to commence <a href="">Continuous Delivery</a> of stories.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Adoption provides coaching essential to getting functional scrums up to speed.
The goal of coaches is always to demonstrate and de-hub, transfrerring
accountability to the actual doers as soon as they&rsquo;re comfortable.</p>

<p>Coaches co-chair meetings, clarify role-specifics, identify misunderstandings
and impediments, configure workflows and knowledge structures, and assure the
team&rsquo;s technical toolset is ready for continuous delivery. They also marshall
metrics and team-member testaments into case studies to support Acceleration.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Acceleration</h4>

<p>Use consensus protocols to iteratively re-energise the tranformation.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Acceleration.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>As agile metrics make productivity and quality gains and challenges
transparent, management focus shifts from &ldquo;how to account for slippage&rdquo; to
&ldquo;how to improve ROI&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>Broken collaboration cycles, structural problems, and <a href="">muda-mura-muri</a>
often occur without the enterprise properly understanding or addressing them.</p></li>
<li><p>Decision makers may say that the transformation has &ldquo;hit a
plateau&rdquo; or experiences pitfalls. They may feel <a href="">FUD</a> about the way ahead.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Re-energize the transformation by promoting consensus mechanisms to capitalize
on wins, address root causes of problems, and refocus on improving the
critical numbers.</p>

<p>Coaches inspect and assure collaboration fundamentals, work with the
Coordination Scrum to address structural issues, and facilitate <a href="">open
spaces</a>, <a href="">agile parliaments</a>, <a href="">lean coffees</a> and <a href="">scrum retros</a> within
guilds and tribes.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Continuous Adaptation</h4>

<p>Refactor the Transformation Roadmap to leverage new capabilities.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Adaptation.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Agility doesn&rsquo;t merely improve productivity and quality metrics.</p></li>
<li><p>New delivery capabilities and new methods of reflection and collaboration
enable qualitative improvements in the way an enterprise organises, grows,
positions, sells and delivers into its marketplace.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Capitalise on these improvements by focusing the Strategic Scrum on
differences between the original <a href="">Agile Transformation Roadmap</a> and the
emergent reality. Gauge these differences with Continuous Assessment metrics
and refactor the transformation roadmap accordingly. Seek out new ways to
integrate internal services, leverage new technologies, form new product lines
and access new market segments. The more often the strategic scrum can review
these things, the faster its enterprise can adapt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile: First Contact]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/11/why-what-how/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T22:59:46+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/11/why-what-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.compelcon.se/gallery/XP2000/XP2000_A_037?full=1">first Alliance
meeting</a> preceded
the famous Snowbird session by almost a year. Sardinia was where <em>Extreme</em>
became <em>Agile</em>. We don&rsquo;t agree on who said it first. It just happened.
Nothing was sacred and no one&rsquo;s ring needed kissing. We were conspirators and
this was a revolution.</p>

<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/Agile-Alliance-XP2K.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why TNG?</h2>

<p>If there were no Agile today we would just invent it all over again, but we
probably wouldn&rsquo;t do it the same way. The Agile Manifesto hasn&rsquo;t changed since
2001. We&rsquo;ve learned a few things since then.</p>

<p>Everyone&rsquo;s seen the <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/background.jpg">Agle Last
Supper</a> picture. With its beautiful
lighting the guys look a lot more credible than half-naked at that first
standup in the Med. Like some kind of saints. But the Mediterranean picture
has more truth. Fallible fellows trying to figure out something bigger than all
of them.</p>

<p>Iconography is important but of course we have lots of agilists these days with
more Agile experience than the Alliance had then. In the 20th century
we&rsquo;d all have cruised over to Ward&rsquo;s Wiki &ndash; when it was the only wiki &ndash; to
share what we&rsquo;re learning in the
<a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNow">WikiNow</a>, that gestalt mind almost but
not entirely unlike Wikipedia. And the Manifesto would have kept evolving.</p>

<p>What happened to the original open community that gave us Agile?  Believe it
or not there was actually a guy who spent the first decade of the 21st century
<a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?GrammarVandal">correcting grammar</a> on C2.
Correcting it <em>wrong</em>. He wasn&rsquo;t alone; there were lots of trolls. Strenuous
efforts were made to salvage C2, but in vain, because when the trolls moved in
the community moved on.</p>

<p>Also some of the original Alliance members became less interested in evolving
the state of the Agile art and more interested in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nsdZKCh6RsU">selling
badges</a>. There seemed no harm in
that at first, but with new players getting in on the action and the
certification businesses booming, it&rsquo;s the opposite of the open spirit of the
Alliance.</p>

<h2>What TNG?</h2>

<p>Agile is about productive teams and their practice patterns, using peer
protocols to self-organise and metric feedback to guide their evolution. Not
badges. The original Manifesto values are as relevant as ever, but that
doesn&rsquo;t mean they shouldn&rsquo;t be refactored and adapted over time the same way
the original open community did. <strong>A:TNG</strong> is for that.</p>

<p>To advance the state of the Agile art we are uncovering, refactoring and
evolving Agile patterns together in a <a href="http://meatballwiki.org/wiki/NonZeroSumGame">Positive Sum
Game</a>. Everyone can play. It
doesn&rsquo;t matter whether or not you&rsquo;ve written a book, earned a certificate or
attended some ancient standup. It only matters that you&rsquo;ve got relevant
experience and ideas to contribute.</p>

<h2>How TNG?</h2>

<p>Consensus generation was the most valuable thing about Ward&rsquo;s Wiki.
Individuals and interactions in open collaboration generated lots of mutually
agreeable content. We might want this old time open Agile back and never mind
trolls and sheriffs &ndash; but how?</p>

<p>A wiki is basically an open version control system wedded to a content editor.
Most are centralized, which means you can only have one current version of
a wiki page at any one time. That&rsquo;s where trolls and sherrifs come from.</p>

<p>On github we have a decentralized VCS as our basis for consensus
decisions. TNG will use this new technology as its way of self-organising. If
any trolls turn up we simply don&rsquo;t need to pull from them. And no more trolls
means no sheriffs.</p>

<p>We could get an <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?AgileParliament">Agile Parliament</a>
going. Treaty proposals as pull requests … that would take some doing. Needs
trial and error, but that’s what we’re here for. To advance the state of our
Agile art.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got lots of basics to cover to give TNG such a form: pick a license, put
up an initial community charter, kick the Parliament pattern around, figure
out how to collaborate on the framing content here, figure out a decenralized
authoring workflow and send out enough invitations to get our kernel community
moving.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s like, when we were kids, we had sea monkeys. The instructions said to add
the sachet to the water and next morning it&rsquo;d be full of little people.
That&rsquo;s our system metaphor for this. Except maybe I&rsquo;m the brine shrimp and
you&rsquo;re the kid wondering when we&rsquo;ll start to look like the picture on the
packet.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s get stuck in. Fork the repo. Help figure the
protocol out. That ol&#8217; <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNature">WikiNature</a>
will kick in real soon &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A:TNG Values]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/10/4-new-values/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T09:43:28+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/10/4-new-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By working Agile and helping others do so we have come to value:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Consensus games over accountable hierarchies</strong></li>
<li><strong>Extreme teams over corporate committees</strong></li>
<li><strong>Stream funding over project budgets</strong></li>
<li><strong>Adaptation patterns over prescriptive frameworks</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>That is, while there is value in the items on the right, we value the items on
the left more. And while we honor the original Manifesto values, we honor these
TNG values equally.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What do those items on the left mean?</h2>

<p>The items on the right are familiar to us all. The items on the left have
a pleasant ring, but let&rsquo;s make some concrete examples to make them clear.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Consensus games</strong> include <a href="">lean coffees</a>, <a href="">open spaces</a>,
<a href="">retrospectives</a>, <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/04/02/iroquois-council/">agile
parliament</a> and other ways
for people to align understandings and make decisions together. Lean coffees
and open spaces do the former; retros and parliaments do the latter.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Extreme teams</strong> are autonomous cross-component cross-functional end-to-end
feature-based teams that self-organize via the <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ExtremeProgrammingCorePractices">XP
rules</a> to optimize
quality, throughput, ROI and alignment of their value stream to its market.
They&rsquo;re extreme in that they consciously &ldquo;turn all the dials to ten&rdquo; to
capitalize on learnings and innovations.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stream funding</strong> means funding to continuously deliver the maximum ROI
features to improve a value stream, rather than chunking objectives,
timeframes and budgets arbitrarily into projects. It includes patterns
from <a href="">Beyond Budeting</a>, <a href="">Beta Codex</a>, and <a href="">Open Book Management</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Adaptation patterns</strong> describe proven solutions to commonplace problems in
a collaborative context. Similar to design patterns for software, they were
pioneered in the initial description of XP and revived by Jim Coplien and
Ken Schwaber in their <a href="">ScrumPLOP</a> conference.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Where do these values come from?</h2>

<p>Agile started with XP on the <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki/ExtremeProgrammingRoadmap">C2
Wiki</a>, a high powered
but open community of professionals sharing patterns and innovations for the
common good. The Agile Alliance distilled this work into a Manifesto and added
a signup page, but C2&rsquo;s open community is the real reason for the global
supremacy of Agile today.</p>

<p>Nevertheless that all happened last century and the Manifesto is showing
its age.  It&rsquo;s still right on when it comes to teams, but lacks values and
principles for large scale Agile adoption. This gap has led to
<a href="http://agile.dzone.com/articles/method-wars-scrum-vs-safe">contention</a> as
consultancies and certificate-mills compete to pry open corporate checkbooks
for their respective brands.</p>

<p>Which is crazy. There&rsquo;s value in both Scrum and SAFe, and no reason to think
you can&rsquo;t combine elements of both along with other frameworks. The value of
frameworks isn&rsquo;t in their brands and certificates, nor in adopting them as
prescriptions, but in adapting the practice patterns they contain.</p>

<p>Schwaber is correct in worrying about the danger of making &ldquo;half a cow and
half a fish&rdquo; when what we really want is dolphins. The question is, on what
basis do you go about the process of adaptation? How do you do it organically,
iteratively, and without tripping up at scale? To do that you need a clear set
of values and principles. And that&rsquo;s where A:TNG comes in.</p>

<p>A:TNG is based on the idea that SAFe, Less, DAD, APF, ETF, OBM, Beyond
Budgeting, Lean and on and on all provide useful adaptation patterns.  And
that there&rsquo;s a lot more to enterprise agility than all of them put together.
We&rsquo;ve augmented the Manifesto values not as a way to make yet another brand,
but as a basis for the work of pulling these pattern languages out of all the
brands and into the open where we can really sort out what works with what.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OAPL: An Open Agile Pattern Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/09/oapl-the-open-agile-pattern-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T18:02:45+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/09/oapl-the-open-agile-pattern-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/images/oapl300.png"></p>

<p>A key activity within A:TNG is organizing an open pattern language to relate
learnings from Agile frameworks to the experiences of our practitioners.
What advantage can this pattern language offer over the original
frameworks? What benefit in a culture where practitioners already have Agile
certificates? Why is this a big deal for TNG?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Pattern Language</h2>

<p>The history of Agile is intertwined with the Design Patterns movement. The
first XP book was framed as a pattern language and while Scrum started as a
framework it is now <a href="http://www.scrumplop.org">reformulating as a pattern
language</a>.</p>

<p>Design patterns started with the great 20th century architect Chris Alexander.
Alexander described them this way: <em>Each pattern describes a problem which
occurs over and over again in our environment, and then describes the core of
a trusted solution to that problem</em>. Alexander&rsquo;s insight was that patterns
work together to generate an architecture as a <a href="http://www.jacana.plus.com/pattern/P0.htm">language of
design</a>.</p>

<p>Software engineers soon took Alexander&rsquo;s idea to a new level with the &ldquo;Pattern
Languages of Programs&rdquo; (<a href="http://hillside.net/conferences">PLoP</a>) conference
series, the best-selling &ldquo;Gang of Four&rdquo; book <a href="http://www.blackwasp.co.uk/GofPatterns.aspx">Design
Patterns</a>, and Ward Cunningham&rsquo;s
<a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?PeopleProjectsAndPatterns">Portland Pattern
Repository</a> which also
became the first wiki, &ldquo;Ward&rsquo;s Wiki&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The success of wiki as a collaborative editing method may have distracted
people from the Pattern Language ideas at its core, but there are still PLoP
conferences every year and popular patterns are known and used by every
professional software engineer.</p>

<p>The key advantage of pattern languages is the empowerment of their users to
make decisions that would otherwise require trial and error or deep expertise.
Furthermore,</p>

<ul>
<li>patterns can be adapted and refactored to suit specific domains without
adopting the pattern language as a whole</li>
<li>patterns enable a process of adaptive design whereby each can by trialled,
added and substracted iteratively as forces in the domain are experienced</li>
<li>the efficacy of alternative patterns can be determined by comparative
studies in related domains, and thereby informed choices can be made.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Anti-Patterns</h2>

<p>The complement to the Design Pattern is the Anti-Pattern, which describes a
solution that fails to solve the problem it was intended to solve, or which
generates more problems.  You may think of anti-patterns as categories of bad
ideas, but another class of them has to do with short term thinking at the
expense of long term goals. This is rather more commonplace than the
conscious bad choices.</p>

<p>In particular in Martin Fowler&rsquo;s book, &ldquo;Refactoring&rdquo;, he and Kent Beck
identify a short list of design problems they call &ldquo;code smells&rdquo;. The code
smells are not bugs &ndash; the code still works &ndash; but a form of design pollution
that makes bugs more likely to occur, and fixing bugs more difficult.</p>

<p>Code smells are often caused by taking shortcuts to get things to work.  As
such they&rsquo;re part of the Agile process. So Beck and Fowler emphasize that it&rsquo;s
not the smells themselves that constitute Anti-Patterns, but a lack of
systematic remediation of them through the critical Agile process of
<a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?RefactorMercilessly">refactoring</a>.</p>

<p>It is unfortunately commmonplace, even in teams that have most of the other
Agile fundamentals nailed down, to find that refactoring is neglected during
times of stress. Of course the less refactoring, the more frequent those
times. The same vicious cycle may occur at the scale of whole organizations,
and so we regard <em>Not Refactoring</em> an &ldquo;Enterprise Smell&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Enterprise Smells &amp; Enterprise Refactorings</h2>

<p>At the level of an Enterprise we don&rsquo;t commonly speak of bugs, but after Lean
we talk of wastes, stressors, irregularities and misalignments. The Lean
movement has produced a classification of the first three of these, and Lean
coaches conduct various practices aimed at reducing them. It is reasonable to
think of Lean as a process of refactoring at an enterprise level.</p>

<p>Lean has not introduced a vocabulary equivalent to that of our Agile
programmers, however, and A:TNG regards this an an opportunity to provide
benefit by filling a gap. As it is reasonable to draw analogies between the
design of an enterprise and the design of a computer program, we can lift each
of the Beck/Fowler code smells into the context of the enterprise without
thinking very hard:</p>

<ul>
<li>duplicated code corresponds with teams with duplicate RACI</li>
<li>long methods correspond with deferred feedback</li>
<li>large classes correspond with large teams or component based teams</li>
<li>too many parameters corresponds with part-time resourcing</li>
<li>and so on &hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>It may be that this is putting the cart before the horse. It would be better
to systematically catalogue enterprise smells and refactorings, and then see
what they have in common with those at a code level. This may form a key
activity of the A:TNG community, and a substantial part of the OAPL may be
devoted to the result. We aim to kick off this cataloguing activity as part of
our inaugural meeting on March 13 in Sydney.</p>

<h2>Pattern Languages over Prescriptive Frameworks</h2>

<p>The reason this value is so prominent in A:TNG isn&rsquo;t to do with Enterprise
patterns and anti-patterns so much as the tendency for enterprises on the
Agile journey to take the advice of experienced agilists for more than it&rsquo;s
worth.</p>

<p>It is reasonable to believe that someone with long experience will have a
valuable practice pattern language to share. It is not reasonable for a guru
to suggest that the patterns in their language are the best, the only, or the
ultimate solution to the problems they address. Outside of the corporate
sphere we regard someone making such claims not as a trustworthy counsellor,
but as a dangerous cult leader. Counsellors explain the key factors in making
decisions; they don&rsquo;t describe the one true path.</p>

<p>It is also reasonable for newcomers to Agile to adopt all the patterns from a
specific framework as their first objective.  As Alistair Cockburn pointed out
in his treatment of <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Shu+Ha+Ri">Shu-Ha-Ri</a>, an
Agile beginner at the Shu level is best advised to follow a single framework
slavishly because that&rsquo;s the only way to experience the behaviour of its
interlocking elements. This is why we say these frameworks have value.</p>

<p>While a framework forms a good starting point for practice, over time the
student develops sufficient understanding of the way the framework applies in
their environment to pass into the realm of &ldquo;Ha&rdquo;. Here reflection and
experimentation with variations and augmentation of the starting framework
becomes the key way to improve, and pattern languages yield their greatest
benefits as signposts along he way.</p>

<p>As the practitioner emerges into the realm of Ri they gain their own insights,
make their own discoveries and solve problems beyond the current state of the
art. And so they&rsquo;re faced with two alternatives. Create a framework of their
own to brand and market the benefit of their learnings, or add their patterns
into an existing pattern language so that other practitioners can test them
against their own experience and refactor them collaboratively. This is the
purpose of the OAPL.</p>

<h2><em>We Are Uncovering Better Ways &hellip;</em></h2>

<p>The latter course may not be so remunerative as the former &ndash; but it is more
Agile because it is more collaborative, more transparent, more scientific, and
more courageous. For this reason the original Agile Manifesto begins with the
words, &ldquo;We are uncovering better ways &hellip;&rdquo;. So does TNG, not out of a sense of
tradition, but because this work of uncovering better ways is our ongoing
mission.</p>

<p>We are uncovering better ways to deliver products and services by improving
our teams, enterprises and communities. And we represent and refactor these
better ways together as patterns in our OAPL. Thereby we make the trade-offs
clear so we can work with newcomers and help them find better ways for
themselves, without expecting them merely to follow in our footsteps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
