<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-10T13:28:58+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 New Values]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/4-new-values/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T09:43:28+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/blog/2014/03/10/4-new-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We boldly identify 4 values Agile needs at enterprise
scale beyond the original manifesto:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Pattern languages over prescriptive frameworks</strong></li>
<li><strong>Productive teams over certified individuals</strong></li>
<li><strong>Metric feedback over command &amp; control</strong></li>
<li><strong>Consensus protocols over management hierarchies</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>That is, while there is value in the items on the right, we value the
items on the left more.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Agile started with XP on the <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki/ExtremeProgrammingRoadmap">C2
Wiki</a>, a high powered
but open community of professionals sharing patterns and innovations for the
common good. The Agile Alliance distilled this work into a Manifesto and added
a signup page, but C2&rsquo;s open community is the real reason for the global
supremacy of Agile today.</p>

<p>But that all happened last century and now the Manifesto is showing its age.
It&rsquo;s still right on when it comes to teams, but lacks values and principles
for large scale Agile adoption. The gap has led to
<a href="http://agile.dzone.com/articles/method-wars-scrum-vs-safe">contention</a> as
consultancies and certificate-mills compete to pry open corporate checkbooks
for their respective brands.</p>

<p>Which is crazy. There&rsquo;s value in both Scrum and SAFe, and no reason to think
you can&rsquo;t combine elements of both along with other frameworks. The value of
frameworks isn&rsquo;t in their brands and certificates, nor in adopting them as
prescriptions, but in understanding and adpting the the practice patterns they
contain.</p>

<p>Schwaber is correct in worrying about the danger of making &ldquo;half a cow and
half a fish&rdquo; when what we really want is dolphins. The question is, on what
basis do you go about the process of adaptation? How do you do it organically,
iteratively, and without tripping up at scale? To do that you need a clear set
of values and principles. And that&rsquo;s where A:TNG comes in.</p>

<p>A:TNG is based on the idea that SAFe, Less, DAD, APF, ETF, OBM, Beyond
Budgeting, Lean and on and on all provide useful patterns.  And that there&rsquo;s a
lot more to enterprise agility than all of them put together. We&rsquo;ve augmented
the Manifesto values not as a way to make yet another brand, but as a basis
for the work of pulling the pattern languages out of all the brands and
into the open where we can really sort out what works with what.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why What How]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/blog/2014/03/09/why-what-how/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T22:59:46+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/blog/2014/03/09/why-what-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why TNG?</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://www.compelcon.se/gallery/XP2000/XP2000_A_037?full=1">stand-up in the
Med</a> that presaged
the famous Snowbird meeting was where <em>Extreme</em> became <em>Agile</em>.  That was
the beauty of it. Nothing was sacred and there was no need to pay our respect
to any great names. We were conspirators and it was a revolution.</p>

<p>If there were no Agile now we would just go and invent it again this way.
What was really great about those early days of the Alliance was there
was no one whose ring needed kissing and change could happen <em>fast</em>.</p>

<p>So how is it that here in 2014 the Manifesto hasn&rsquo;t changed since 2001?  There
are conferences every year; have we learned nothing in all this time? Seeing
the Manifesto as some historical document like the Declaration of Independence
just doesn&rsquo;t seem very &hellip; Agile.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We all know the <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/background.jpg">Agle Last Supper
picture</a>. The truth is there are
lots of agilists these days with more experience than the Snowbird guys had
back then. In the 20th century we&rsquo;d have cruised over to Ward&rsquo;s Wiki &ndash; when it
was the only wiki &ndash; to share what we were learning in the
<a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNow">WikiNow</a>, that gestalt mind almost but
not entirely unlike Wikipedia. And the Manifesto would have kept evolving.</p>

<p>What happened to that first open Agile community? Believe it or not there was
actually a guy who spent the first decade of the 21st century <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?GrammarVandal">correcting
grammar</a> on C2. Correcting it
<strong>wrong</strong>. He wasn&rsquo;t alone; there were lots of trolls. Strenuous efforts were
made to salvage C2 but it was in vain, because when the trolls moved in the
community moved on.</p>

<p>Likewise some of the original Alliance members seem less interested in
evolving Agile in the open and more interested in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nsdZKCh6RsU">playing police and wearing
badges</a>. There are new players
acting like <em>federales</em> too, and the badge business seems to be booming.</p>

<h2>What TNG?</h2>

<p>Agile was never about badges. It&rsquo;s about productive teams and their practice
patterns, using peer protocols to self-organise and metric feedback to guide
their evolution. The original Manifesto values are still relevant and
valuable, but that doesn&rsquo;t mean they shouldn&rsquo;t be refactored and adapted the
same way the original open community did. <strong>A:TNG</strong> is for that.</p>

<p>To advance the state of the Agile art we will discover, refactor and evolve
Agile patterns together in a <a href="http://meatballwiki.org/wiki/NonZeroSumGame">Positive Sum
Game</a>. Everyone can play. It
doesn&rsquo;t matter whether or not you&rsquo;ve written a book, earned a badge or
attended some ancient standup. It only matters that you&rsquo;ve got relevant
experience and useful ideas to contribute.</p>

<h2>How TNG?</h2>

<p>Consensus generation was the most valuable thing about Ward&rsquo;s Wiki.
Individuals and interactions in open collaboration generated lots of mutually
agreeable content. We might want this old time open Agile back and never mind
trolls and sheriffs &ndash; but how?</p>

<p>A wiki is basically an open version control system wedded to a content editor.
Most are centralized, which means you can only have one current version of
a wiki page at any one time. That&rsquo;s where trolls and sherrifs come from.</p>

<p>On github we have a decentralized VCS as our basis for consensus
decisions. TNG will use this new technology as its way of self-organising. If
any trolls turn up we simply don&rsquo;t need to pull from them. And no more trolls
means no sheriffs.</p>

<p>We could get an <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?AgileParliament">Agile Parliament</a>
going. Treaty proposals as pull requests … that would take some doing. Needs
trial and error, but that’s what we’re here for. To advance the state of our
Agile art.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got lots of basics to cover to give TNG such a form: pick a license, put
up an initial community charter, kick the Parliament pattern around, figure
out how to collaborate on the framing content here, figure out a decenralized
authoring workflow and send out enough invitations to get our kernel community
moving.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s like, when we were kids, we had sea monkeys. The instructions said to add
the sachet to the water and next morning it&rsquo;d be full of little people.
That&rsquo;s our system metaphor for this. Except maybe I&rsquo;m the brine shrimp and
you&rsquo;re the kid wondering when we&rsquo;ll start to look like the picture on the
packet.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s get stuck in. Star and fork the repo. Help figure the
protocol out. That ol&#8217; <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNature">WikiNature</a>
will kick in real soon &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
