<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Patterns | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/patterns/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-24T10:11:54+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OAPL: An Open Agile Pattern Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/09/oapl-the-open-agile-pattern-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-09T18:02:45+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/09/oapl-the-open-agile-pattern-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/oapl300.png"></p>

<p>A key activity within A:TNG is organizing an open pattern language to relate
learnings from Agile frameworks to the experiences of our practitioners.
What advantage can this pattern language offer over the original
frameworks? What benefit in a culture where practitioners already have Agile
certificates? Why is this a big deal for TNG?</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Pattern Language</h2>

<p>The history of Agile is intertwined with the Design Patterns movement. The
first XP book was framed as a pattern language and while Scrum started as a
framework it is now <a href="http://www.scrumplop.org">reformulating as a pattern
language</a>.</p>

<p>Design patterns started with the great 20th century architect Chris Alexander.
Alexander described them this way: <em>Each pattern describes a problem which
occurs over and over again in our environment, and then describes the core of
a trusted solution to that problem</em>. Alexander&rsquo;s insight was that patterns
work together to generate an architecture as a <a href="http://www.jacana.plus.com/pattern/P0.htm">language of
design</a>.</p>

<p>Software engineers soon took Alexander&rsquo;s idea to a new level with the &ldquo;Pattern
Languages of Programs&rdquo; (<a href="http://hillside.net/conferences">PLoP</a>) conference
series, the best-selling &ldquo;Gang of Four&rdquo; book <a href="http://www.blackwasp.co.uk/GofPatterns.aspx">Design
Patterns</a>, and Ward Cunningham&rsquo;s
<a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?PeopleProjectsAndPatterns">Portland Pattern
Repository</a> which also
became the first wiki, &ldquo;Ward&rsquo;s Wiki&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The success of wiki as a collaborative editing method may have distracted
people from the Pattern Language ideas at its core, but there are still PLoP
conferences every year and popular patterns are known and used by every
professional software engineer.</p>

<p>The key advantage of pattern languages is the empowerment of their users to
make decisions that would otherwise require trial and error or deep expertise.
Furthermore,</p>

<ul>
<li>patterns can be adapted and refactored to suit specific domains without
adopting the pattern language as a whole</li>
<li>patterns enable a process of adaptive design whereby each can by trialled,
added and substracted iteratively as forces in the domain are experienced</li>
<li>the efficacy of alternative patterns can be determined by comparative
studies in related domains, and thereby informed choices can be made.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Anti-Patterns</h2>

<p>The complement to the Design Pattern is the Anti-Pattern, which describes a
solution that fails to solve the problem it was intended to solve, or which
generates more problems.  You may think of anti-patterns as categories of bad
ideas, but another class of them has to do with short term thinking at the
expense of long term goals. This is rather more commonplace than the
conscious bad choices.</p>

<p>In particular in Martin Fowler&rsquo;s book, &ldquo;Refactoring&rdquo;, he and Kent Beck
identify a short list of design problems they call &ldquo;code smells&rdquo;. The code
smells are not bugs &ndash; the code still works &ndash; but a form of design pollution
that makes bugs more likely to occur, and fixing bugs more difficult.</p>

<p>Code smells are often caused by taking shortcuts to get things to work.  As
such they&rsquo;re part of the Agile process. So Beck and Fowler emphasize that it&rsquo;s
not the smells themselves that constitute Anti-Patterns, but a lack of
systematic remediation of them through the critical Agile process of
<a href="http://c2.com/cgi-bin/wiki?RefactorMercilessly">refactoring</a>.</p>

<p>It is unfortunately commmonplace, even in teams that have most of the other
Agile fundamentals nailed down, to find that refactoring is neglected during
times of stress. Of course the less refactoring, the more frequent those
times. The same vicious cycle may occur at the scale of whole organizations,
and so we regard <em>Not Refactoring</em> an &ldquo;Enterprise Smell&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Enterprise Smells &amp; Enterprise Refactorings</h2>

<p>At the level of an Enterprise we don&rsquo;t commonly speak of bugs, but after Lean
we talk of wastes, stressors, irregularities and misalignments. The Lean
movement has produced a classification of the first three of these, and Lean
coaches conduct various practices aimed at reducing them. It is reasonable to
think of Lean as a process of refactoring at an enterprise level.</p>

<p>Lean has not introduced a vocabulary equivalent to that of our Agile
programmers, however, and A:TNG regards this an an opportunity to provide
benefit by filling a gap. As it is reasonable to draw analogies between the
design of an enterprise and the design of a computer program, we can lift each
of the Beck/Fowler code smells into the context of the enterprise without
thinking very hard:</p>

<ul>
<li>duplicated code corresponds with teams with duplicate RACI</li>
<li>long methods correspond with deferred feedback</li>
<li>large classes correspond with large teams or component based teams</li>
<li>too many parameters corresponds with part-time resourcing</li>
<li>and so on &hellip;</li>
</ul>


<p>It may be that this is putting the cart before the horse. It would be better
to systematically catalogue enterprise smells and refactorings, and then see
what they have in common with those at a code level. This may form a key
activity of the A:TNG community, and a substantial part of the OAPL may be
devoted to the result. We aim to kick off this cataloguing activity as part of
our inaugural meeting on March 13 in Sydney.</p>

<h2>Pattern Languages over Prescriptive Frameworks</h2>

<p>The reason this value is so prominent in A:TNG isn&rsquo;t to do with Enterprise
patterns and anti-patterns so much as the tendency for enterprises on the
Agile journey to take the advice of experienced agilists for more than it&rsquo;s
worth.</p>

<p>It is reasonable to believe that someone with long experience will have a
valuable practice pattern language to share. It is not reasonable for a guru
to suggest that the patterns in their language are the best, the only, or the
ultimate solution to the problems they address. Outside of the corporate
sphere we regard someone making such claims not as a trustworthy counsellor,
but as a dangerous cult leader. Counsellors explain the key factors in making
decisions; they don&rsquo;t describe the one true path.</p>

<p>It is also reasonable for newcomers to Agile to adopt all the patterns from a
specific framework as their first objective.  As Alistair Cockburn pointed out
in his treatment of <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/Shu+Ha+Ri">Shu-Ha-Ri</a>, an
Agile beginner at the Shu level is best advised to follow a single framework
slavishly because that&rsquo;s the only way to experience the behaviour of its
interlocking elements. This is why we say these frameworks have value.</p>

<p>While a framework forms a good starting point for practice, over time the
student develops sufficient understanding of the way the framework applies in
their environment to pass into the realm of &ldquo;Ha&rdquo;. Here reflection and
experimentation with variations and augmentation of the starting framework
becomes the key way to improve, and pattern languages yield their greatest
benefits as signposts along he way.</p>

<p>As the practitioner emerges into the realm of Ri they gain their own insights,
make their own discoveries and solve problems beyond the current state of the
art. And so they&rsquo;re faced with two alternatives. Create a framework of their
own to brand and market the benefit of their learnings, or add their patterns
into an existing pattern language so that other practitioners can test them
against their own experience and refactor them collaboratively. This is the
purpose of the OAPL.</p>

<h2><em>We Are Uncovering Better Ways &hellip;</em></h2>

<p>The latter course may not be so remunerative as the former &ndash; but it is more
Agile because it is more collaborative, more transparent, more scientific, and
more courageous. For this reason the original Agile Manifesto begins with the
words, &ldquo;We are uncovering better ways &hellip;&rdquo;. So does TNG, not out of a sense of
tradition, but because this work of uncovering better ways is our ongoing
mission.</p>

<p>We are uncovering better ways to deliver products and services by improving
our teams, enterprises and communities. And we represent and refactor these
better ways together as patterns in our OAPL. Thereby we make the trade-offs
clear so we can work with newcomers and help them find better ways for
themselves, without expecting them merely to follow in our footsteps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
