<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Values | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/values/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-31T14:59:43+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A:TNG Values]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/10/4-new-values/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T09:43:28+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/10/4-new-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By working Agile and helping others do so we have come to value:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Consensus protocols over accountable hierarchies</strong></li>
<li><strong>Productive teams over certified authorities</strong></li>
<li><strong>Evolving pattern languages over prescriptive frameworks</strong></li>
<li><strong>Capability funding over project funding</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>That is, while there is value in the items on the right, we value the items on
the left more. And while we honor the original Manifesto values, we honor these
values equally.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Agile started with XP on the <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki/ExtremeProgrammingRoadmap">C2
Wiki</a>, a high powered
but open community of professionals sharing patterns and innovations for the
common good. The Agile Alliance distilled this work into a Manifesto and added
a signup page, but C2&rsquo;s open community is the real reason for the global
supremacy of Agile today.</p>

<p>Nevertheless that all happened last century and the Manifesto is showing
its age.  It&rsquo;s still right on when it comes to teams, but lacks values and
principles for large scale Agile adoption. This gap has led to
<a href="http://agile.dzone.com/articles/method-wars-scrum-vs-safe">contention</a> as
consultancies and certificate-mills compete to pry open corporate checkbooks
for their respective brands.</p>

<p>Which is crazy. There&rsquo;s value in both Scrum and SAFe, and no reason to think
you can&rsquo;t combine elements of both along with other frameworks. The value of
frameworks isn&rsquo;t in their brands and certificates, nor in adopting them as
prescriptions, but in understanding and adpting the the practice patterns they
contain.</p>

<p>Schwaber is correct in worrying about the danger of making &ldquo;half a cow and
half a fish&rdquo; when what we really want is dolphins. The question is, on what
basis do you go about the process of adaptation? How do you do it organically,
iteratively, and without tripping up at scale? To do that you need a clear set
of values and principles. And that&rsquo;s where A:TNG comes in.</p>

<p>A:TNG is based on the idea that SAFe, Less, DAD, APF, ETF, OBM, Beyond
Budgeting, Lean and on and on all provide useful patterns.  And that there&rsquo;s a
lot more to enterprise agility than all of them put together. We&rsquo;ve augmented
the Manifesto values not as a way to make yet another brand, but as a basis
for the work of pulling the pattern languages out of all the brands and
into the open where we can really sort out what works with what.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
