<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: enterprise | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/enterprise/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-26T09:46:41+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Seven Samurai]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T21:53:27+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A pattern language for enterprise agile transformation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Agreement.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Spoilers</h2>

<p>Akira Kurosawa&rsquo;s cinematic masterpiece provides a great <a href="">system metaphor</a> for
Enterprise Agile transformation and thereby the fundamental pattern language of the <a href="">OAPL</a>.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to see the film to understand the pattern language, but these
patterns necessarily involve spoilers for the film. So you may want to see it
first if you haven&rsquo;t already.  The restored 207-minute version is freely
available on <a href="http://thepiratebay.se/search/seven%20samurai/0/7/0">&ldquo;iTunes&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>From here on out we&rsquo;ll leave the question of spoilage up to you, gentle
reader.</p>

<h2>The Film</h2>

<p><em>The Seven Samurai</em> concerns a defenceless village that hires a group of
down-at-heel samurai as protection against a horde of bandits. The samurais
transform the village into a force that destroys the bandits and takes
ownership of its own destiny.</p>

<p>The popular image of samurai as armored warriors is quite different to the way
they&rsquo;re depicted here. Kurosawa&rsquo;s samurai are master strategists, coaches of
the first water. While they are hands on and assist with every step of the
transformation, in the end, as their leader says, it&rsquo;s the village that wins,
not the samurai.</p>

<p>Close inspction shows the transformation involves 9 distinct strategic
patterns, each of which will be augmented with more detailed tactical
patterns. We&rsquo;ve discussed construction of an Agile pattern language <a href="">here</a>
and here we employ the <a href="http://c2.com/ppr/about/portland.html">Portland Form</a>
in this due to its simplicity.</p>

<p>Why eight patterns when there are only seven samurai? Simply, the last pattern
is for the enterprise to take ownership of its own transformation as coaching
becomes irrelevant. As in the film, it&rsquo;s the village that wins, not the
samurai.</p>

<hr />

<h2>The Patterns</h2>

<h4>Assessment</h4>

<p>Motivate Agile in terms of bottom line metrics.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Assessment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Many organisations embark on Agile ad-hoc, at grass roots level, without
clearly understandng real drivers, benefits and challenges.</p></li>
<li><p>Enterprise architecture and business constraints can prevent Agile
transformation from succeeding. Some enterprises may not be ready to
commit to addressing these constraints.</p></li>
<li><p>Teams, programs and business units may begin a transformation without
realising their organisation isn&rsquo;t ready, and this may lead them to fail.</p></li>
<li><p>Prominent failures may forestall a successful transformation, creating the
perception that Agile &ldquo;might work elsewhere but can&rsquo;t work here&rdquo;.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Interview stakeholders to construct preliminary value stream maps of delivery
and business activities. Validate these by attending the represented
activities and constructing cumulative flow metrics for them.</p>

<p>Diagram these to motivate urgent concern about waste, stress, irregularity and
misalignment. Determine critical numbers that represent real improvements to
throughput, quality and ROI.</p>

<p>Construct a preliminary plan detailing targets for these critical numbers with
a draft timeframe and budget necessary to transform to a Minimum Viable Agile
Capability (&ldquo;MVAC&rdquo;) that would meet these targets, at least on a small scale.</p>

<p>Assess maturity of existing Agile teams using the <a href="http://comparativeagility.com">Cohn&rsquo;s Comparative Agility
metrics</a>, and reconcile with the MVAC.</p>

<p>See also <a href="">Goose in the Bottle</a></p>

<hr />

<h4>Alignment</h4>

<p>Align relevant decision makers to form a Strategic Scrum.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Alignment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Component silos, matrix management, waterfall baselines and phase gates,
project based cost accounting and middle management hierarchies can make it
difficult for an organisation to achieve and understand Agile benefits.</p></li>
<li><p>There are further alignment issues inherent in a transformation program.
Progressive/conservative antagonism, disagreements over change scope and
ownership, confusion over metrics and trade-offs, as well as the FUD induced
by piecemeal change &hellip;</p></li>
<li><p>Enterprise misalignments are commonly associated with the anti-patterns
we call <a href="">enterprise smells</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Ad hoc Agile teams can&rsquo;t address such alignment issues because they don&rsquo;t
have adequate executive support to change the process of other teams or the
way they interoperate.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Induce progressive senior executives to meet regularly in a collaborative
&ldquo;Strategic Scrum&rdquo; that maintains product ownership of the transformation.</p>

<p>Ideally execs are motivated to participate by pre-existing C-level support.
Such support is seldom reliable at the start of a transformation, however, and
it may be an urgent priority of the Strategic Scrum to enrol enterprise
coaching expertise to obtain it.</p>

<p>The object of this support is to simply establish ownership of the
transformation as resting with the Strategic Scrum. As with Agile delivery,
the senior member of the scrum is identified as Chief Product Owner for
the transformation, with the others dubbed <a href="">Operational Product Owners</a>.</p>

<p>This Strategic Scrum provides a way for executives to immediately experience
agile for themselves and <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?EatYourOwnDogfood">eat their own
dogfood</a> and provides a one stop
shop into which coaches and organisational change agents report progress.</p>

<p>See also <a href="">Guiding Coalition</a>, <a href="">Influence the Influencers</a>, <a href="">Inversino of
Control</a></p>

<hr />

<h4>Analysis</h4>

<p>Form a Coordination Scrum from coaches and delivery and operational stream
leads.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Analysis.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Once an enterprise has assessed as-is state and aligned executives
to support its transformation, there is an immediate desire for detailed
OCM plans.</p></li>
<li><p>Under time pressure OCM may prefer a one-size-fits-all framework and an
idealistic &ldquo;to-be state&rdquo; vision. A BDUF focus on vision and framework over
iterative progress maximises WIP and results in dysfunctional transition
states where delivery and business metrics consistently worsen, and appetite
for change wanes.</p></li>
<li><p>OCM plans may also be applied in a non-collaborative &ldquo;they change, we
don&rsquo;t&rdquo; mindset. If change agents are not also change recipients they are
insensitive to the wisdom of the doers causing widespread <a href="">FUD</a> and politics.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>To make an enterprise Agile, we emphasise that change planning must be Agile.
What&rsquo;s wanted isn&rsquo;t a precise vision but a disciplined collaboration cycle for
a funded Coordination Scrum that includes existing stream leads. That&rsquo;s to say
lead doers, not middle-management deciders, along with experienced coaches to
provide sound advice on tactical concerns over the course of the transformation.</p>

<p>The Coordination Scrum represents its work on a <a href="">Agile Transformation
Roadmap</a> from which coaches derive a <a href="">Coaching Kanban</a> that prioritises
and tracks their team-based coaching activities, and which is iteratively
reviewed by the transformation product owners of the Strategic Scrum.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Awareness</h4>

<p>Organise change recipients into a system of <a href="">Guilds and Tribes</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Awareness.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Change plans usually begin with training for the doers on new ways of
working.  This includes role-specific skills and education on the tools
necessary to new roles.</p></li>
<li><p>Awareness as a process isn&rsquo;t merely a matter of training, but ongoing
agreement about ways of working, For the transformation to become
sustainable, doers must own and direct the change stories themselves.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Organise people of common capabilities into &ldquo;Guilds&rdquo; and people collaborating
on common business and delivery streams into &ldquo;Tribes&rdquo;. Let coaches work with
these teams to plan and effect change using a repeating cycle of Scrum
<a href="">retrospectives</a> and, at scale, <a href="">agile parliaments</a>.</p>

<p>These consensus protocols spread awareness of the drivers and methods for new
ways of working, and feed decisions, agreements and concerns back into the
Coordination Scrum.</p>

<p>Coaches use role-playing games to raise Guild and Tribe awareness of Agile
methods and their respective parts in the transformation.  The Coordination
Scrum also works with the Strategic Scrum to obtain support to empower tribes
and guilds to make their own decisions to enable rapid change.</p>

<p>Once they&rsquo;re up to speed, add Guild and Tribe representatives to the
Coordination Scrum. If scale requires it, the Coordination Scrum may evolve
into a Guild in its own right.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Architecture</h4>

<p>Guilds institute technical enablers for feature based delivery.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Architecture.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Technical enablers and structural transformations must be adopted by
change recipients to enable new ways of working.</p></li>
<li><p>Change patterns promoted by the Coordination Scrum have to be grounded and
tailored into stories that fit the immediate necessities of the as-is
enterprise.</p></li>
<li><p>Change stories that requires anyone to down tools will be immediately
opposed by the guild system and business stakeholders.</p></li>
<li><p>Collaborative coaching is necessary to assure change recipients are ready
and motivated to work in the new way</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Prioritize technical enablers in the Coaching Kanban including
* work-management and knowledge-management tools
* test data fixtures and service mock objects
* BDD tooling and integration of same into dev workflow
* virtual environments sufficient for Continuous Delivery
* version control systems suitable for distributed integration.</p>

<p>At an enterprise level prioritise structural transformation patterns including</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="">Goose in the Bottle</a></li>
<li><a href="">Feature Based Teams</a></li>
<li><a href="">Behavioural Product Planning</a></li>
<li><a href="">Inversion of Control</a></li>
<li><a href="">Capability Funding</a></li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h4>Adoption</h4>

<p><img src="/images/Adoption.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Track transformation stories in a coaching kanban.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Coaching shepherds product planning and delivery teams through the same
Samurai patterns as it does for the enterprise, just on a smaller scale.</p></li>
<li><p>A well formed transformation plan involves a backlog of <a href="">Transformation
Stories</a> motivated by drivers identified by <a href="">Operational Product Owners</a>
from the Strategic Scrum.  These stories should have the <a href="">INVEST</a>
properties and be expected to demonstrate value by improving
<a href="#Assessment">Assessmet</a> metrics.</p></li>
<li><p>ROI for Agile transformation is maximized when transformation stories are
detailed and delivered iteratively, minimizing <a href="">Work In Progress</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Value delivery begins as the <a href="">Product Planning Scrum</a> builds a
breadth-first product roadmap and an initial product backlog along with a
&ldquo;Steel Thread&rdquo; sufficient to commence <a href="">Continuous Delivery</a> of stories.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Adoption provides coaching essential to getting functional scrums up to speed.
The goal of coaches is always to demonstrate and de-hub, transfrerring
accountability to the actual doers as soon as they&rsquo;re comfortable.</p>

<p>Coaches co-chair meetings, clarify role-specifics, identify misunderstandings
and impediments, configure workflows and knowledge structures, and assure the
team&rsquo;s technical toolset is ready for continuous delivery. They also marshall
metrics and team-member testaments into case studies to support Acceleration.</p>

<hr />

<h4>Acceleration</h4>

<p><img src="/images/Acceleration.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Use consensus protocols to re-energise the tranformation.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>As agile metrics make productivity and quality gains and challenges
transparent, management focus shifts from &ldquo;how to account for slippage&rdquo; to
&ldquo;how to improve ROI&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>Broken collaboration cycles, structural problems, and muda-mura-muri
often occur without the enterprise properly understanding or addressing them.</p></li>
<li><p>Decision makers may say that the transformation has &ldquo;hit a
plateau&rdquo; or experiences pitfalls. They may feel <a href="">FUD</a> about the way ahead.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Re-energize the transformation by promoting consensus mechanisms to capitalize
on wins, address root causes of problems, and refocus on improving the
critical numbers.</p>

<p>Coaches inspect and assure collaboration fundamentals, work with the
Coordination Scrum to address structural issues, and facilitate <a href="">open
spaces</a>, <a href="">agile parliaments</a>, <a href="">lean coffees</a> and <a href="">scrum retros</a> within
guilds and tribes.</p>

<hr />

<h4><a href="Adaptation"></a>Adaptation</h4>

<p><img src="/images/Adaptation.png" width="400"></p>

<p>Refactor the transformation canvas to leverage new capabilities.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Agility doesn&rsquo;t merely improve productivity and quality metrics.</p></li>
<li><p>New delivery capabilities and new methods of reflection and collaboration
enable qualitative improvements in the way an enterprise organises, grows,
positions, sells and delivers into its marketplace.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Capitalise on these improvements by focusing the Strategic Scrum on
differences between the original <a href="">Agile Transformation Roadmap</a> and the
emergent reality. Gauge these differences with the Assessment metrics and
refactor the roadmap accordingly. Seek out new ways to integrate
internal services, form new product lines and access new market segments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
