<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Alignment | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/alignment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-10T12:24:17+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Merel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Problem With Projects]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/13/product-funding/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T20:15:15+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/04/13/product-funding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/nails.png" width="400"></p>

<p>When all you have is a hammer, every problem looks like a nail.  When all you
have is a project management methodology, everything looks like a project. </p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Most organisations have become very project focussed. Everything is a project.
New release of software – project. Some process change – project. That’s
great. Projects are good. They are certainly better than the ad-hoc approach
we had before projects. But projects do have some drawbacks.</p>

<p>To work out what the drawbacks are, we need to look at what a project is. A
project is defined (by the PMI who should know) as something that has a
defined scope, a defined start and a defined end date.  So projects are finite
in length. Anything without an end date isn’t a project, it’s business as
usual.</p>

<p>This defined end date is where the problem with projects lies. In reality,
most of the things we treat as projects aren’t really projects. They have no
real end date. Let’s take software delivery as an example. A company develops
a product, let’s call it “Wonder Widget”. They want to release a new version
(WW 2.0) so they start a WW2.0 project with an end date that matches the
desired release date. When the release date is reached, the project team is
disbanded. Then when they want to release WW2.1, they start up the WW2.1
project and so on. Sound familiar? The industry does this all the time. So
what’s the problem?</p>

<p>The problem is that these aren’t really separate pieces of work. Development
of Wonder Widget doesn’t stop when 2.0 is released; it continues. But in a
project-focussed world, the team that developed 2.0 is not necessarily the
same as the team that develops 2.1. Project teams have a finite life. Some of
the key members may be the same but many will be off on other projects (Super
Service 3.5) so the new team has to learn about Wonder Widget from scratch.</p>

<p>Even worse, the Wonder Widget 2.0 team may have left things in a bad state. We
all know how this happens - schedule pressure near the end of a project. The
team feels stressed. There are still new features to deliver. Other things
start to slip. Like testing and documentation and code quality. All the things
that will make life really hard for the 2.1 team.  The 2.0 team won’t be
judged on how clean they leave things for 2.1, or on how much technical debt
they accrue. They will be judged on how successful 2.0 is – how many features
it has, how well it sells. Everyone knows that 2.1 will have a hard time but
hey, that’s their problem. 2.0 will be a great success.</p>

<p>Sound familiar? </p>

<p>The problem with projects like this is that they aren’t really projects.</p>

<h2 id="therefore">Therefore</h2>

<p>Treat Product development as a continuous activity. </p>

<p><img src="/images/zipper.png"></p>

<p>One release of a product shouldn’t mess up the organisation’s ability to
deliver the next release. What we need is a Product focus rather than a
Project focus. The team shouldn’t be the 2.0 team, they should be the Wonder
Widget team. They should be responsible for all the releases of the product.
They should flow from one release to the next as a stable team.</p>

<p>Quite obviously this removes the learning stage from the beginning of each
release but more importantly “that’s their problem” suddenly becomes “that’s
our problem”. The team now has an incentive to keep quality high. This flows
on to other organisational benefits like more predictable releases (as teams
are’t blindsided by technical debt left behind by other teams rushing to
finish).</p>

<p>Similarly for change management projects. Running change management as a
project is a great way to ensure that the change fades away as soon as the
project is finished. Change management is ongoing, with no real end date.</p>

<p>Projects are fine for things that are actually projects. But let’s stop
treating everything like one.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
