<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alignment | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/alignment/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-31T13:48:09+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Goose In The Bottle]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-27T11:31:11+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Take a newly hatched baby goose. Poke it down the neck of an empty saki bottle
and feed it till it&rsquo;s grown. Without killing the goose or breaking the bottle,
how do you get the goose out of the bottle?</p>

<p><img src="/images/gib.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the problem and the solution in context and leave the riddle
till after.</p>

<h2>Pattern in Portland Form</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>A team can only change as quickly as its most conservative member. A program
of component teams or an organization of silos can only change as rapidly as
its most conservative part.</p></li>
<li><p>Every team has its progressives. If they&rsquo;re empowered, they foster
change. If they&rsquo;re disempowered, they&rsquo;re still eager to take part in change.</p></li>
<li><p>Middle managers account for costs and apologise for slippage. They&rsquo;re used
to that. Telling them to account for ROI and taking away their apologetic
method causes the infamous <a href="">Frozen Middle</a> anti-pattern.</p></li>
<li><p>Taking a team, program or organization part-way Agile offers questionable
benefit and creates risks of failure and reversion to tradition. Taking part
of it part-way reduces the benefit and amplifies the risks.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t attempt to make an enterprise become Agile. Nor a program, nor a
project, nor a team.</p>

<p>Instead, create a new cross-functional end-to-end feature based Agile
capability uncompromised by existing ways of working.</p>

<p>Staff it with progressives And grow it with the support of a coordination
scrum of lead doers from the old organisation with the blessing of senior
management.</p>

<p>Let it leverage the quickest dirtiest deployment pathway but make it
accountable for its own quality.</p>

<p>Add product owners focused on maximising ROI per release rather than
minimising variance to baseline.</p>

<p>Put in place bottom-line metrics to demonstrate that the throughput, quality
and ROI of the new capability exceeds the performance of the old.</p>

<p>Never ask anyone to join the new capability, but let the best people do so,
backfilling the old organisation if necessary, letting it diminish otherwise.</p>

<h2>Zen Riddles</h2>

<p>The Goose in the Bottle is what the Japanese Zen tradition calls a <em>koan</em>, a
kind of riddle for personal transformation. It&rsquo;s not supposed to have a
rational answer.</p>

<p>Solving it is supposed to take sweat. You may have to travel. Consult wise
people. Spend days in silent meditation. Raise children and learn from them.
Grok out.</p>

<p>You&rsquo;re a busy person, however, and this is about Agile, not Zen, so I&rsquo;ll just
give you the answer so we can move on.</p>

<h2>The Coach in the Bottle</h2>

<p>I first read the goose koan as a young man. I puzzled over it for weeks but
then set it aside.  Who has time for a riddle with no answer? I thought it
could have no practical importance and I had no shortage of more interesting
questions to worry about.</p>

<p>Until, as a coach, I became a goose.</p>

<p>I accepted a role transforming a business unit of the largest Australian
insurer. A year earlier I had successfully transformed an insurance BI group
of about seventy. Now I had three hundred staff stuck in silos and component
layers, with myself the sole coach charged with getting them out.</p>

<p>This insurer had attempted ad-hoc Agile twice. Its first project went cowboy,
shipping 5 months late with 1200 defects and zero documentation. The second
project used Agile to fail fast, demonstrating its business case didn&rsquo;t stand
up. For which learning it was blamed and shamed, and its excellent
Scrum-master got handed her hat.</p>

<p>I naturally expect to walk into this kind of thing. A coach is only engaged
when management strikes a problem it can&rsquo;t solve without a coach. You expect to
walk into trouble, or else you won&rsquo;t be there in the first place.</p>

<p>Per the <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/">seven samurai</a> I
set about assessing and aligning senior business and delivery management and
also technical leads per silo.  That&rsquo;s when I hit the wall. People were happy
to engage with me, but I was getting the same conversation over and over. Six
times in a week according to my diary.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I completely agree with you,&rdquo; they said. &ldquo;Agile is great. If we could do
it properly, life would be much better. But you&rsquo;ll never get <em>them</em> to do it.&rdquo;</p>

<p>They&rsquo;d point out another team. I would talk to that team and <em>they</em> would say
the same about further teams, who would point back at teams I&rsquo;d already spoken
to.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t blamestorming &ndash; it was respect for their conservative co-workers.
Each team has conservatives and progressives, and no team can change faster
than its most conservative member. The progressives had learned that through
bitter experience.</p>

<p>That was the bottle, and I was the goose.</p>

<h2>Grow a Better Gosling</h2>

<p>Some mornings I woke in a cold sweat. I realised we were all geese in some
way. The managers who hired me, the progressives who wanted change, but
the conservatives too. They all made up each others' bottle.</p>

<p>In my previous role, on a smaller scale and with sufficient executive support,
I had been able to break a bottle. But this one was too strong. I wasn&rsquo;t going
to kill the goose by quitting either. So now I really needed an answer &hellip; how
did those old Zen guys get their damned goose out of their damned bottle?</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lovely and controversial Zen book called <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Sound-One-Hand-Answers/dp/0465080782">The Sound of the One
Hand</a>, which
poses answers to 281 Zen Koans. It offers the following for this one:</p>

<p><strong>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s out!&rdquo;</strong></p>

<p>I found that answer a little unhelpful. In fact I have yet to derive any
assistance from that book in regard to any koan. Which is to say it&rsquo;s a
really great zen book and I highly recommend it.</p>

<p>In a flash, enlightenment occurred, that experience Zen students spend
their time desperately attempting to attain. Or if it wasn&rsquo;t enlightenment, it
would do until enlightenment came along.</p>

<p><em>Take a baby goose, a newly hatched gosling. Feed it outside the bottle until
it&rsquo;s full grown. Feel your heart swell as you watch it flying away.</em></p>

<p>This is to say, don&rsquo;t attempt to make an enterprise become Agile. Nor a
program, nor a project, nor a team. Instead, create a new cross-functional
end-to-end feature based Agile capability for the enterprise uncompromised by
any existing ways of working. And then grow it.</p>

<p>Feed it a budget, requirements, and team members drawn from the progressive
people you&rsquo;ve assessed in interviews. Form a coordination scrum of stream
leaders from the old organisation, empowered by senior management not to
change how the old organisation works, but just to support the new capability.</p>

<p>Let the new capability leverage the quickest dirtiest deployment pathway that
exists for hotfixing. Make them accountable for their own quality and go whole
hog on virtual environments and test-first automation. Use a DVCS to manage
integration between old and new rationally. Add  product owners focused on
maximising ROI in the backlog rather than minimising variance to baseline.</p>

<p>Coach this tiny new capability to produce just the minimum amount of
documentation necessary to satisfy their own operational members. Don&rsquo;t call
it a goose, but something completely innocuous, &ldquo;the small changes team&rdquo; or
similar.</p>

<p>Put in place bottom-line metrics to demonstrate that the throughput, quality
and ROI of the new team far exceeds the performance of teams in the jugged
goose.  Promote and leverage their wins to gain them more requirements from
the business.</p>

<p>Never ask anyone to join the new capability, but let the best people do so,
backfilling the old organisation if necessary, letting it diminish otherwise.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how I coached. Over the course of a year that first gosling grew
organically, splitting and splitting again. Business people saw concrete
benefit and flocked together. The coordination forum used this as a model to
create similar goslings. They grew fat and laid golden eggs &hellip;</p>

<h2>The Ugly Duckling</h2>

<p>Two years later the insurer&rsquo;s senior management turned up at Australia&rsquo;s
largest Agile conference to trumpet their wins. Still I wondered &ndash; is this a
reproducible pattern? I soon had a chance to find out.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very large bank, the twentieth largest corporation in the world.
Long before that insurance gig I&rsquo;d been engaged as a coach to take a couple of
its projects Agile. I didn&rsquo;t use the <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/">seven
samurai</a> then, just got
stuck in and went for it.</p>

<p>While we made progress we were stopped by unaligned senior management when
they found out what we were up to.  My coaching sponsors were none too pleased
that I hadn&rsquo;t addressed alignment before moving onto adoption. The
experience turned ugly and I never expected to be invited back.</p>

<p>Well, never say never. Six years later I was re-engaged by the same senior
manager who&rsquo;d handed me my hat. We had both learned in the interim, and he had
an ad-hoc Agile project in the online division that was struggling.</p>

<p>This project was for a ground-breaking product, but it was perceived to have
under-delivered its first release with severe quality problems. I found all
manner of waste, stress, compromise and misalignment. But there was one great
advantage. This product was regarded as special. That little team was already
out of the bottle.</p>

<p>Over the next 18 months I aligned the rest of the business unit to support the
new capability and mentored the team directly to consistently exceed their
metrics release on release. The product won a dozen external awards and the
team received the Group CIO award for best project in the bank.</p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t all me of course &ndash; the team members were all-stars. But it was never
a perfect project. There were hard yards to make. Nevertheless, realignment of
delivery pipeline, team structure and environment management that resulted
became a model to be leveraged. First within the online program, then within
its business unit, and then throughout the bank.</p>

<p>Sorry, but I can&rsquo;t resist talking about the waterfowl method here &hellip;
comparing Agile in the bank with Aesop&rsquo;s <a href="http://hca.gilead.org.il/ugly_duc.html">ugly
duckling</a> who grew up &hellip;  and then
everyone saw it as a beautiful swan &hellip;</p>

<h2>Will it Zen?</h2>

<p>In a <a href="http://alistair.cockburn.us/The+Goose+in+the+Bottle">conversation with Alistair
Cockburn</a> I explained my
experience with this Goose In the Bottle pattern. He worried that I had
&ldquo;[broken] the question’s presupposition by cheating and getting a new goose,
hence not answering the question, but still ending up a free goose.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I wanted to point Alistair at the <a href="http://www.markability.net">laws of form</a>
but I didn&rsquo;t get time. Of course it requires only a moment&rsquo;s thought to
realize there can never be a real goose in a real bottle. If you did it
to a real gosling, it would perish long before it grew old enough to poke
its head out. Our goose was always a metaphor.</p>

<p>On the zen of it, the moment you hear this koan some part of you becomes the
goose, and the koan your bottle. Like all koans, to get out you have to change
who you are.</p>

<p>The bottle doesn&rsquo;t break &ndash; the old organisation never changes. The goose
doesn&rsquo;t have to be killed &ndash; neither in the bottle nor out of it. But as you
feed the goose outside more requirements and more budget and more people,
soon there is no goose left in the bottle. Nor a bottle for it to be in.</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s out!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
