<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: coaching | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/coaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-28T11:15:36+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Peter Merel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Seven Samurai]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T21:53:27+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/21/the-seven-samurai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Enterprise Agile is a phrase that’s bandied about a lot.  What is it, why would you
want it, and how do you get it? The Seven Samurai neatly answers those questions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Agreement.jpg"></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>In an ever-accelerating marketplace it has become common sense that businesses must
continously adapt to avoid being outcompeted by others. On a small scale the process
of adaptation can be dealt with by regular Scrum retrospectives and the Demming cycle.
A significant program or business unit, however, cannot adapt piece-meal or it risks
all the Lean sins of stress, irregularity and waste.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#the-patterns">The Patterns</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#continuous-assessment">Continuous Assessment</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-alignment">Continuous Alignment</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-analysis">Continuous Analysis</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-awareness">Continuous Awareness</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-architecture">Continuous Architecture</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-adoption">Continuous Adoption</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-acceleration">Continuous Acceleration</a></li>
      <li><a href="#continuous-appropriation">Continuous Appropriation</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Let’s define enterprise agility as continuous adaptation. Adaptation of internal
structure and process as delivery capabilities evolve.  Adaptation of external value
streams to customer experiences, market forces and technological innovations.
Adaptation of these two to each other to maximise product-market fit and ROI. </p>

<p>This obviously applies during process transformation but for enterprise agility
continous adaptation must continue even after new process elements are bedded down.
The Seven Samurai pattern language provides a proven framework for doing just that.</p>

<h2 class="no_toc" id="spoilers">Spoilers</h2>

<p>You don’t need to see the Kurosawa film to understand the pattern language, but its
patterns necessarily involve spoilers so you may want to see the film first.  The
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zNqQXC8Tv8U">restored version</a> is available through
the usual streaming sites so we’ll leave the question of spoilage to you, gentle
reader. </p>

<h2 class="no_toc" id="the-film">The Film</h2>

<p>The Seven Samurai concerns a defenceless village that hires a group of down-at-heel
samurai as protection against a horde of ruthless bandits. The samurai efficiently
transform the village into a self-organising force to destroy the bandits and take
ownership of its own destiny. </p>

<p>Our Western image of samurai as armored warriors is very different to their depiction
here. Kurosawa’s samurai are really seven coaches, each embodying a distinct strategic
pattern, each reinforcing the others so that the whole becomes greater than the sum of
its parts.</p>

<p>Why eight patterns when there are only seven samurai? The last pattern represents the
end of the film where the village takes ownership of its own transformation and
external coaching becomes irrelevant. Per the final line of the film, it’s the village
that wins, not the samurai.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-patterns">The Patterns</h2>

<h3 id="continuous-assessment">Continuous Assessment</h3>

<p>Motivate Agile in terms of continuous evaluation of bottom line metrics.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Assessment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Many organisations embark on Agile ad-hoc, at grass roots level, without clearly
understanding real drivers, benefits and challenges.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Enterprise architecture and business constraints can prevent Agile transformation
from succeeding. Many enterprises are not ready to commit to addressing these
constraints.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Teams, programs and business units may begin a transformation without realising
their organisation isn’t ready, and this in itself may lead them to fail.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Prominent failures may forestall further transformation, creating the perception
that Agile “might work elsewhere but can’t work here”.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Interview stakeholders to construct preliminary value stream maps of delivery and
business activities. Validate these by attending the represented activities and
instrument cumulative flow metrics for them.</p>

<p>Represent these metrics as diagrams to motivate urgent concern about waste, stress,
irregularity and misalignment. Determine critical numbers that would represent
achievable Agile improvements to throughput, quality and ROI.</p>

<p>Construct a preliminary plan detailing targets for these critical numbers with a draft
timeframe and budget necessary to generate the Minimum Viable Agile Capability
(“MVAC”) that would meet those targets on a small scale.  Assess maturity of existing
mission-critical teams using the <a href="http://comparativeagility.com">Cohn’s Comparative Agility
metrics</a>, and compare with the MVAC.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-alignment">Continuous Alignment</h3>

<p>Enrol decision makers as Product Owners in an iterative “Strategic Scrum” that meets
at least weekly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Alignment.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Component silos, matrix management, waterfall baselines and phase gates, project
based cost accounting and middle management hierarchies can make it difficult for an
organisation to host and maintain Agile feature teams. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>There are further alignment issues inherent in a transformation program.
Progressive/conservative antagonism, disagreements over change scope and ownership,
confusion over metrics and trade-offs, as well as the simple
<a href="http://www.cavcomp.demon.co.uk/halloween/fuddef.html">FUD</a> of a reaction to change
… </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Enterprise misalignments are commonly associated with the anti-patterns we call
<a href="">enterprise smells</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Ad hoc Agile teams can’t address such alignment issues because they don’t have
adequate executive support to change the process of other teams or the way they
interoperate.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Induce progressive senior executives to meet regularly in a collaborative “Strategic
Scrum” whose mission is product ownership for the transformation.  </p>

<p>Ideally, execs are motivated to participate by pre-existing C-level support.  Such
support is seldom reliable at the start of a transformation, however, and it may be an
urgent priority of the Strategic Scrum to leverage the output of the Assessment
pattern to demonstrate sufficient drivers to establish funding and ownership of a
transformation initiative.</p>

<p>The Strategic Scrum provides a way for the executives to immediately experience agile
for themselves and <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?EatYourOwnDogfood">“eat their own
dogfood”</a>. Over the course of the
transformation it will provide a one stop shop into which coaches and organisational
change agents report progress, and change its membership and form as required to fit
the evolving agile enterprise.</p>

<p>An important first step for the Strategic Scrum is selecting one or more 
alignment patterns to form the initial stage of the transformation:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/03/27/the-goose-in-the-bottle/">Goose in the
Bottle</a></li>
  <li><a href="">Inversion of Ownership</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/vmysla/scrum-at-spotify">Tribes and Guilds</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://scaledagileframework.com/investment-themes/">Stream Funding</a></li>
  <li><a href="">Lean before Agile</a></li>
  <li>… </li>
</ul>

<p>See also <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/04/21/xscale/#feature-points">Behavioural Product
Planning</a>, <a href="">Feature Based
Teams</a> <a href="http://www.kotterinternational.com/our-principles/changesteps/step-2">Guiding
Coalition</a>,
<a href="">Influence the Influencers</a></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-analysis">Continuous Analysis</h3>

<p>Form a Coordination Scrum from coaches and delivery and operational stream
leads that meets at least weekly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Analysis.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Once an enterprise has assessed its as-is state and aligned executives
to support its transformation, there is an immediate desire for a detailed
“to-be” vision and a plan to get there. This is often called an OCM
(“Organisation Change Management”) plan. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Under time pressure, the people accountable for OCM may feel safest picking a
one-size-fits-all framework and idealistic “to-be state” vision. This is
a waterfall approach to transformation - what XP used to call “Big Design 
Up Front” or “BDUF”. We call it “Big Change Up Front” or BCUF.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sounds nasty but why is it actually bad? BCUF focus on vision and
framework maximises WIP and results in dysfunctional transition states where
delivery and business metrics consistently worsen. This obviously raises
risks and can cause executive support for transformation to tail off.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>OCM plans may also be applied in a non-collaborative “they change, we
don’t” mindset. If change agents are not also change recipients they are
insensitive to the wisdom of the doers causing widespread <a href="">FUD</a> and politics.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>To make an enterprise Agile, we emphasise that change planning must be Agile.  What’s
needed isn’t a precise vision but an iterative collaboration cycle for a “Coordination
Scrum” that begins with just the  existing stream leads. That’s to say lead doers, not
middle-management deciders, along with experienced coaches to provide insight on
tactical concerns over the course of the transformation.</p>

<p>The primary accountability of the Coordination Scrum is enabling the new agile
delivery stream to efficiently integrate with existing component streams. This work is
represented on an <a href="">Agile Transformation Roadmap</a> from which coaches derive a
<a href="">Coaching Kanban</a> to prioritise and track their coaching activities per team.
Cumulative flow of this kanban is iteratively reviewed by the transformation product
owners of the Strategic Scrum.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-awareness">Continuous Awareness</h3>

<p>Organise change recipients into a system of <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/vmysla/scrum-at-spotify">Guilds and
Tribes</a>. Represent each tribe at
the weekly Coordination Scrum.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Awareness.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Change plans usually begin with training for the doers on new ways of
working.  This includes role-specific skills and education on the tools
necessary to new roles.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Awareness as a process isn’t merely a matter of training, but ongoing
agreement about ways of working, For the transformation to become
sustainable, doers must own and direct the change stories themselves.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Organise people of common capabilities into “Guilds” and people collaborating on
common business and delivery streams into “Tribes” or “Streams”. Let coaches work with
these teams to plan and effect change using a weekly cycle of Scrum
<a href="http://fabiopereira.me/blog/2008/11/23/goal-driven-retrospective/">retrospectives</a>
and, at scale, <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/04/02/iroquois-council/">stream councils</a>. </p>

<p>These consensus protocols spread awareness of drivers and methods for new ways of
working, and feed decisions, agreements and concerns back into the Coordination Scrum. </p>

<p>Coaches use role-playing games to raise Guild and Tribe awareness of Agile methods and
their respective parts in the transformation.  The Coordination Scrum also works with
the Strategic Scrum to obtain support to empower tribes and guilds to make their own
decisions to enable rapid change.</p>

<p>Once they’re up to speed, add Guild and Tribe representatives to the Coordination
Scrum. At scale, the Coordination Scrum may evolve into an <a href="http://agiletng.org/2014/04/21/xscale/#continuous-adaptation">Enterprise
Council</a></p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-architecture">Continuous Architecture</h3>

<p>Guilds meet weekly to institute technical enablers for feature based delivery.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Architecture.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Technical enablers and structural transformations must be adopted by 
change recipients to enable new ways of working. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Change patterns promoted by the Coordination Scrum have to be grounded and
tailored into stories that fit the immediate necessities of the as-is
enterprise. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Change stories that requires anyone to put down their tools and stand idle
will be immediately opposed by the guild system and business stakeholders. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Collaborative coaching is necessary to assure change recipients are ready
and motivated to work in the new way</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Prioritize technical enablers in the Coaching Kanban including but not limited
to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>work-management and knowledge-management tools </li>
  <li>test data fixtures and service mock objects</li>
  <li>BDD tooling and integration of same into dev workflow</li>
  <li>virtual environments sufficient for Continuous Delivery</li>
  <li>version control systems suitable for distributed integration.</li>
</ul>

<p>At an enterprise level, Guilds stage the structural alignment patterns
determined by the Strategic Scrum, assure existing component teams are primed
to support if not adopt the new ways of working, and that scarce technical
resources or SMEs are adequately available for new delivery capabilities to
come on line.</p>

<p>At first guilds adopt, specialise, adjust and refactor architectural patterns
iteratively as they gain experience with the benefits and challenges.  As the Agile
capability grows, however, guilds naturally split into chapters per tribe, each of
which is empowered to make these autonomous decisions for its tribe. As this occurs
each chapter will be represented at its own stream council, and Guild meetings
may become less frequent.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-adoption">Continuous Adoption</h3>

<p>Coaches track transformation stories in a coaching kanban and report weekly to
coordination and strategic scrums.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Adoption.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Coaching shepherds product planning and delivery teams through the same
Samurai patterns as it does for the enterprise, just on a smaller scale.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>A well formed transformation plan involves a backlog of <a href="">Transformation
Stories</a> motivated by drivers identified by <a href="">Operational Product Owners</a>
from the Strategic Scrum.  These stories should have the <a href="">INVEST</a>
properties and be expected to demonstrate value by improving
<a href="#Assessment">Assessment</a> metrics. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>ROI for Agile transformation is maximized when transformation stories are
detailed and delivered iteratively, minimizing <a href="">Work In Progress</a>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Value delivery begins as the <a href="">Product Planning Scrum</a> builds a
breadth-first product roadmap and an initial product backlog along with a
<a href="">Steel Thread</a> sufficient to commence <a href="">Continuous Delivery</a> of stories.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Adoption provides coaching essential to getting functional scrums up to speed.
The goal of coaches is always to demonstrate and de-hub, transfrerring
accountability to the actual doers as soon as they’re comfortable.</p>

<p>Coaches co-chair meetings, clarify role-specifics, identify misunderstandings
and impediments, configure workflows and knowledge structures, and assure the
team’s technical toolset is ready for continuous delivery. They also marshall
metrics and team-member testaments into case studies to support Acceleration.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-acceleration">Continuous Acceleration</h3>

<p>Use consensus protocols to iteratively re-energise the tranformation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Acceleration.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>As agile metrics make productivity and quality gains and challenges
transparent, management focus shifts from “how to account for slippage” to
“how to improve ROI”. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Broken collaboration cycles, structural problems, and <a href="">muda-mura-muri</a>
often occur without the enterprise properly understanding or addressing them. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Decision makers may say that the transformation has “hit a
plateau” or experiences pitfalls. They may feel <a href="">FUD</a> about the way ahead.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Re-energize the transformation by promoting consensus mechanisms to capitalize
on wins, address root causes of problems, and refocus on improving the
critical numbers.</p>

<p>Coaches inspect and assure collaboration fundamentals, work with the
Coordination Scrum to address structural issues, and facilitate <a href="">open
spaces</a>, <a href="">Iroquois Councils</a>, <a href="">lean coffees</a> and <a href="">scrum retros</a> within
guilds and tribes.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="continuous-appropriation">Continuous Appropriation</h3>

<p>Refactor the Transformation Roadmap to leverage new capabilities.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Adaptation.png" width="400"></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Agility doesn’t merely improve productivity and quality metrics. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>New delivery capabilities and new methods of reflection and collaboration
enable qualitative improvements in the way an enterprise organises, grows,
positions, sells and delivers into its marketplace. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Such new capabilities require new resource funding that is not borrowed piece-meal
from other streams.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Therefore,</strong></p>

<p>Capitalise on these improvements by focusing the Strategic Scrum on
differences between the original <a href="">Agile Transformation Roadmap</a> and the
emergent reality. </p>

<p>Gauge these differences with Continuous Assessment metrics and refactor the
transformation roadmap accordingly. Consider new ways to integrate internal services,
leverage new technologies, form new product lines and access new market segments. </p>

<p>Use <a href="">Roadmap Refactoring</a> to determine which of these initiatives offer the maximum
benefit to existing value streams, and over what timeframes. Treating the existing
value streams as customers for new capabilities, let representatives of each determine
the proportion of their own revenues they’re willing to share with other streams,
including any new streams that may be required to field the new capabilities.</p>

<p>The more often the strategic scrum can review these things, the faster its enterprise
can adapt.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
