<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meta | Agile: The Next Generation]]></title>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/categories/meta/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-26T09:41:35+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[A:TNG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Agile: First Contact]]></title>
    <link href="http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/11/why-what-how/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-11T22:59:46+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://Agile-TNG.github.io/2014/03/11/why-what-how</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.compelcon.se/gallery/XP2000/XP2000_A_037?full=1">first Alliance
meeting</a> preceded
the famous Snowbird session by almost a year. Sardinia was where <em>Extreme</em>
became <em>Agile</em>. We don&rsquo;t agree on who said it first. It just happened.
Nothing was sacred and no one&rsquo;s ring needed kissing. We were conspirators and
this was a revolution.</p>

<p><img src="/images/Agile-Alliance-XP2K.png"></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Why TNG?</h2>

<p>If there were no Agile today we would just invent it all over again, but we
probably wouldn&rsquo;t do it the same way. The Agile Manifesto hasn&rsquo;t changed since
2001. We&rsquo;ve learned a few things since then.</p>

<p>Everyone&rsquo;s seen the <a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/background.jpg">Agle Last
Supper</a> picture. With its beautiful
lighting the guys look a lot more credible than half-naked at that first
standup in the Med. Like some kind of saints. But the Mediterranean picture
has more truth. Fallible fellows trying to figure out something bigger than all
of them.</p>

<p>Iconography is important but of course we have lots of agilists these days with
more Agile experience than the Alliance had then. In the 20th century
we&rsquo;d all have cruised over to Ward&rsquo;s Wiki &ndash; when it was the only wiki &ndash; to
share what we&rsquo;re learning in the
<a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNow">WikiNow</a>, that gestalt mind almost but
not entirely unlike Wikipedia. And the Manifesto would have kept evolving.</p>

<p>What happened to the original open community that gave us Agile?  Believe it
or not there was actually a guy who spent the first decade of the 21st century
<a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?GrammarVandal">correcting grammar</a> on C2.
Correcting it <em>wrong</em>. He wasn&rsquo;t alone; there were lots of trolls. Strenuous
efforts were made to salvage C2, but in vain, because when the trolls moved in
the community moved on.</p>

<p>Also some of the original Alliance members became less interested in evolving
the state of the Agile art and more interested in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nsdZKCh6RsU">selling
badges</a>. There seemed no harm in
that at first, but with new players getting in on the action and the
certification businesses booming, it&rsquo;s the opposite of the open spirit of the
Alliance.</p>

<h2>What TNG?</h2>

<p>Agile is about productive teams and their practice patterns, using peer
protocols to self-organise and metric feedback to guide their evolution. Not
badges. The original Manifesto values are as relevant as ever, but that
doesn&rsquo;t mean they shouldn&rsquo;t be refactored and adapted over time the same way
the original open community did. <strong>A:TNG</strong> is for that.</p>

<p>To advance the state of the Agile art we are uncovering, refactoring and
evolving Agile patterns together in a <a href="http://meatballwiki.org/wiki/NonZeroSumGame">Positive Sum
Game</a>. Everyone can play. It
doesn&rsquo;t matter whether or not you&rsquo;ve written a book, earned a certificate or
attended some ancient standup. It only matters that you&rsquo;ve got relevant
experience and ideas to contribute.</p>

<h2>How TNG?</h2>

<p>Consensus generation was the most valuable thing about Ward&rsquo;s Wiki.
Individuals and interactions in open collaboration generated lots of mutually
agreeable content. We might want this old time open Agile back and never mind
trolls and sheriffs &ndash; but how?</p>

<p>A wiki is basically an open version control system wedded to a content editor.
Most are centralized, which means you can only have one current version of
a wiki page at any one time. That&rsquo;s where trolls and sherrifs come from.</p>

<p>On github we have a decentralized VCS as our basis for consensus
decisions. TNG will use this new technology as its way of self-organising. If
any trolls turn up we simply don&rsquo;t need to pull from them. And no more trolls
means no sheriffs.</p>

<p>We could get an <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?AgileParliament">Agile Parliament</a>
going. Treaty proposals as pull requests … that would take some doing. Needs
trial and error, but that’s what we’re here for. To advance the state of our
Agile art.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got lots of basics to cover to give TNG such a form: pick a license, put
up an initial community charter, kick the Parliament pattern around, figure
out how to collaborate on the framing content here, figure out a decenralized
authoring workflow and send out enough invitations to get our kernel community
moving.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s like, when we were kids, we had sea monkeys. The instructions said to add
the sachet to the water and next morning it&rsquo;d be full of little people.
That&rsquo;s our system metaphor for this. Except maybe I&rsquo;m the brine shrimp and
you&rsquo;re the kid wondering when we&rsquo;ll start to look like the picture on the
packet.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s get stuck in. Fork the repo. Help figure the
protocol out. That ol' <a href="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WikiNature">WikiNature</a>
will kick in real soon &hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
